<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter: whearin, part of the entertainment vntoo the Queenz Maiesty, at Killingwoorth Castl, in Warwick Sheér, in this soomerz progress 1575. iz signified: from a freend officer attendant in the coourt, vnto his freénd a citizen, and merchaunt of London</title>
            <author>Patten, William, fl. 1548-1580.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15191</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108211</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843883</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843883</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 255:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter: whearin, part of the entertainment vntoo the Queenz Maiesty, at Killingwoorth Castl, in Warwick Sheér, in this soomerz progress 1575. iz signified: from a freend officer attendant in the coourt, vnto his freénd a citizen, and merchaunt of London</title>
                  <author>Patten, William, fl. 1548-1580.</author>
                  <author>Laneham, Robert, 16th cent, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 54, 56-87 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: R.L. Gent mercer, i.e. Robert Laneham; but in fact by William Patten.</note>
                  <note>A satire in Warwickshire dialect.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Social life and customs --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:8645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Book plate reflecting previous ownership by John Perceval</figDesc>
                  <head>SUB CRUCE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>AN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
                  <p>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Percivale Baronet of Burton in the County of Cork in Ireland.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER:</p>
            <p>Whearin, part of the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vntoo the Queenz Maieſty, at Killingwoorth Caſtl, in Warwik Shéer in this Soomerz Progreſſ 1575. iz ſignified: from a freend officer attendant in the Coourt, vntoo hiz fréend a Citizen, and Merchaunt of London.</p>
            <q>
               <l>DE REGINA NOSTRA ILLVSTRISSIMA.</l>
               <l>Dum laniata rua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vicina ab Regna tumultu:</l>
               <l>Laeta ſuos inter genialibus ILLA diebus,</l>
               <l>(Gratia Dijs) fruitur: Ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pantur &amp; ilia Codro.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <add>
                  <q>
                     <l>While that oour neighboourz <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>amz (aſaid) vprore dooth rend aſunder,</l>
                     <l>In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th amoong the ſubiects that her Maieſty an Vnder,</l>
                     <l>She (thanks too God) leads pleazaunt daiz: let ſpite &amp; mallis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q>
               </add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8645:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8645:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntoo my good freend, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Humfrey Martin Mercer.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter my hartie</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacionz, I commende mee hartily too yoo. Vnderſtande yée, that ſins throogh God &amp; good fréends, I am placed at Coourt héer (as yée wot) in a woorwipfull room: whearby, I am not onlie acquainted with the moſt, and well knoen too the beſt, and euery officer glad of my company: but alſo haue poour, a dayz (while the Councell ſits not) to go and too ſée things ſight worthy, and too bée prezent at any ſheaw or ſpectacl, only whear this Progreſſe reprezented vnto her highneſſ: And of part of which ſportez, hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin ſum notez and obſeruationz (for I can not bée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dl at ony hand in the world) az well too put fro me ſuſpition of ſluggardy, az too pluk from yoo doout of ony my forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of fréendſhip: I haue thought it méet too impart them vntoo yoo, az frankly, az fréendly, and az fully az I can. Well wot yée the blak Prins waz neuer ſtained with diſloyaltee of ingratitude towarde ony, I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8645:3"/>
dare bee his warrant hee will not beginne with yoo that hath at hiz hand ſo déeply de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerued.</p>
            <p>But héerin, the better for conceyuing of my minde and inſtruction of yoors, ye muſt gyue mee leaue a littl, az well to preface vntoo my matter, az to diſcoors ſumwhat of Killyng woorth Caſtl. A Territory of the right honorabl, my ſingular good Lord, my Lord the Earl of Leyceter: of whooz incomparabl cheeryng, and enterteynment thear vntoo her Maieſty noow, I will ſhew yoo a part heer, that coold not ſée all, nor had I ſeen all coold well report the hallf: Whear thynges, for the parſons, for the place, time, coſt, deuiſez, ſtraungnes, and aboundauns of all that euer I ſawe (and yet haue I been, what vnder my Maſter Bomſted, and what on my oun affayres, whyle I occupied Merchaundize, both in Frauns and Flaunders (long and many a day) I ſaw none ony where ſo memorabl, I tell you plain.</p>
            <p>The Caſtl hath name of Killingwoorth, <note place="margin">Killing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorth Caſtl.</note> but of truth grounded vppon feythfull ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Kenelwoorth. It ſtonds in Warwyk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyre, a lxxiiii. myle northweſt from Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and az it wear in the Nauell of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8645:3"/>
foure myle ſumwhat South from Couentree a proper Cittee, and a lyke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauns from Warwyk, a fayre Sheere Tonn on the North: In ayr ſweet and hollſum, raiſed on an eazy mounted hill, iz ſette eeuenlie coaſted with the froont ſtraight intoo the Eaſt, hath the tenaunts and Tooun about it, that pleaſantly ſhifts from dale too Hyll ſundry whear wyth ſweet Springs burſting foorth: and iz ſo plentifullie well ſorted on euery ſide intoo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>arabl, meado, paſture, wood, water, &amp; good ayr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> az it appeerz to haue need of nothing that may perteyn too liuing or pleazure. Too auauntage hath it, hard on the Weſt, ſtill nouriſht with many liuely Springs, a goodly Pool of rare beauty, bredth, length, deapth, and ſtore of all kinde freſh water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, delicat, great and fat, and alſo of wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fooul byſide. By a rare ſituacion and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral amitee ſeemz this Pool conioynd to the Caſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that on the Weſt layz the head az it wear vpon the Caſtlz booſom, embraceth it on either ſide Soouth and North with both the armz, ſettlz it ſelf az in a reach a flightſhoot brode, ſtretching foorth body and legs a myle or too Weſtward: between a fayre Park on the one ſide, which by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8645:4"/>
Braiz is linked too the caſtl on the South, ſprinckled at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entrauns with a feaw Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyez, that for colour and ſmallnes of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſéem too bée ſuffered more for pleaſure then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditée: And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oother ſide, North and Weſt, a goodlie Chaſe: waſt, wyde, large, and full of red Déer and oother ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie gamez for hunting: beautified with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie delectabl, freſh &amp; vmbragioous Boowz, Arberz, Seatz, and walks, that with great art, coſt, &amp; diligens wear very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zauntly appointed: which alſo the naturall grace by the tall and freſh fragrant tréez &amp; ſoil did ſo far foorth comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, az <hi>Diana</hi> her ſelfe might haue deyned thear well enough too raunge for her paſtime. The leaft arme of this pool Northward, had my Lorde adoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urned with a beautifull bracelet of a fayr tymbred bridge, that iz of xiiii. foot wide, and a ſix hundred foot long: railed all on both ſidez, ſtrongly planked for paſſage, reaching from the Chaſe too the Caſtl: that thus in the midſt hath clear proſpect ouer théez pleaſurz on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> backpart: and forward, ouer all the Toun and mooch of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trée beſide. Héertoo, a ſpeciall commoditee at hand of ſundrie quarreiz of large buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtone, the goodnes whearof may the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8645:4"/>
eazlyar be iudged, in the bilding and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienty of the Caſtl, that (az by the name &amp; by ſtoriez, well may be gathered) waz firſt reared by <hi>Kenulph</hi> and hiz young ſun and ſucceſſor <hi>Kenelm:</hi> born both indeed within the Ream héer, but yet of the race of Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Florileg. fo.</hi> 221. <hi>&amp;</hi> 225.</note> and reigned kings of Marchlond fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yeer of oour Lord. 798. too. 23. yéerz too<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther, aboue 770. yéer ago. Although the Caſtl hath one auncient ſtrong and large Kéep that iz called Ceazarz Tour, rather (az I haue good cauz to think) for that it iz ſquare and hye foormed after the maner of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Guil. Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſb. li.</hi> 1.</note> Cezarz Fortz then that euer he bylt it. Nay noow I am a littl in, Maſter Martin ile tell you all.</p>
            <p>This Marchlond that Storyerz call <hi>Mercia,</hi> iz numbred in their bookes, the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urth of the ſeauen Kingdomes that the Saxons had whilom heer diuided among them in the Ream. Began in <hi>Anno Domi.</hi> 616. 139. yéer after <hi>Horſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Engiſt,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the race of a 17. kings. a. 249. yéer togyther: and ended in <hi>Ann.</hi> 875. Reyzed from the reſt (ſayz the book) at firſt by <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daz</hi> prezumption: ouerthroun at laſt by <hi>Buthreds</hi> Haſcardy, and ſo fel to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doom of the Weſt Saxons.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8645:5"/>
And Marchlond had in it, London, Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delſex, <note place="margin">Mercia.</note> héerin a Biſhoprik. Had more of Shyrez: Gloceter, Woorceter, and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wik, and héerin a Biſhoprik. Cheſter (that noow we call Cheſſhyre) Darby and Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord, whervntoo one Biſhop that had alſo part of Warwik and Shrewſbery and hiz See at Couentree, that waz then afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time at Lychfeeld. Héertoo: Hereford, wherin a Biſhoprik that had more too iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, half Shreuſbury, part of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wik and alſo of Gloceter, and the See at Hereford. Alſo had Oxford, Buckingham, Hertford, Huntingdon, and halfe of Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, and too theez, Norhampton, part of Lecyter and alſo Lincoln, whearvnto a Biſhop: whoz See at Lincoln Citee that ſumtime before waz at Dorcheſter. Héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too, the reſt of Leyceter &amp; in Nottingham that of olld had a ſpeciall Biſhop, whooz See waz at Leyceter, but after, put to the charge of the Archbiſhop of Yorke.</p>
            <p>Noow touching the name, that of olld Recordes I vnderſtand, and of auncient writers I finde, iz calld <hi>Kenelvvorth.</hi> Syns moſt of the <hi>Worths</hi> in England ſtand ny vntoo like lakez, and at eyther ſmall Ilandz, ſuch one az the ſeat of this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8645:5"/>
Caſtl hath béen &amp; eazly may bee, or is lond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground by pool or riuer whearon willoz, alderz or ſuch like doo gro: which <hi>Altha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vpon Taci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fol.</hi> 142. <hi>The Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains call werk that we</hi> woork. Worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-woorld. <hi>We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mut:</hi> woorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood. So <hi>viel vvor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> So much woorth.</note> writez precizely that the Germains cal Werd: Ioyning theſe too togither with the nighneſſ allſo of the woords and ſybred of the toongs. I am the bolder to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noouns, that az our Engliſh <hi>Woorth,</hi> with the reſt of oour auncient langage, waz leaft vs from the Germains: éeuen ſo that their Werd and our <hi>Woorth</hi> iz all one thing in ſignifiauns, common too vs both éen at this day. I take the caſe ſo cléer that I ſay not az mooch as I moought. Thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face ye with the Preface. And noow to the matter.</p>
            <p>ON Saterday the nyenth of Iuly, at long Ichington, a Tooun and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of my Lords, within a ſeaven myle of Killingworth, hiz honor made her Maieſty great chéer at Dinner, and pleazaunt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime in hunting by the wey after, that it was eight a clock in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euening ear her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſ came too Killingwoorth. Whear in the Park, about a flight ſhoot from the Brayz &amp; firſt gate of the Caſtl, one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ten Sibills, that (wée réed) wear all <hi>Fatidicae</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obulae<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sibyl.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:8645:6"/>
(az partiez and priuy too the Gods gracious good wilz (cumly clad in a pall of white ſylk, pronounced a proper poezi in Engliſh rime and méeter: of effect hoow great gladneſſe her hyghneſſe prezenze brought into euerie ſteed whear it pleazed her too cum, and ſpecialli now into that place that had ſo long longed after the ſame: en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with propheſie certain, of mooch and long proſperitée health and felicitée: this her Maieſtie beningly acceptying, paſſed fooorth vntoo the next gate of the Brayz, which (for the length, largenes and vſe (az well it may ſo ſerue) they call noow the Tyltyard, whear a Porter, tall of perſon, <note place="margin">The Porter</note> big of lim &amp; ſtearn of coountinauns, wrapt alſo all in ſilke, with a club &amp; keiz of qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titée according: had a rough ſpeech full of paſſions in méeter aptly made to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: whearby (az her highnes was cum within his warde) hée burſt out in a great pang of impatiens to ſée ſuch vncooth trud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging too and fro, ſuch riding in and out, with ſuch dyn and noiz of talk within the charge of his offis: whearof hee neuer ſaw the like nor had any warning afore, ne yet coold make too himſelfe any cauze of the matter, at laſt vpon better vieu and auiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8645:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
az hee preaſt too cum neerar: confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing anon that hee found him ſelf pearced at the prezens of a perſonage ſo euidently expreſſing an heroicall Soueraintee ouer all the whole eſtates, &amp; hy degréez thear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde: callmd hiz ſtomz, proclaims open gates and frée paſſage to all, yéelds vp hiz club, hiz heyz, hiz office and all, and on hiz knéez humbly prayz pardon of hiz igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauns and impaciens: which her highnes graciouſlie graunting, he cauzd hiz Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petoourz <note place="margin">The Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petoours.</note> that ſtood vppon the wall of the gate thear, too ſoound vp a tune of wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum: which, beſyde the nobl noyz, was ſo mooch the more pleazaunt too behold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauz théez Trumpetoourz beeing ſixe in number, wear euery one an eight foot hye, in due proportion of parſon beſyde, all in long garments of ſylk ſutabl, eache with hiz ſyluery Trumpet of a fiue foot long, foormed Taperwyſe, and ſtraight from the vpper part vntoo the neather eend: whear the Diameter was a 16. ynchez ouer and yet ſo tempered by art, that being very eazy too the blaſt, they caſt foorth no greater noyz nor a more vnpleazaunt ſoound for time and tune, then any oother common Trumpet bee it neuer ſo artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8645:7"/>
foormed. Theeſe armonious blaſterz, from the foreſide of the gate at her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes entrauns whear they began: walking vpon the wallz, vntoo the inner: had this muzik mainteined from them very delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably while her highneſſ all along this tilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard rode vnto the inner gate next the baſe coourt of the Caſtl: where the Lady of the Lake (famous in king Arthurz book) with <note place="margin">Lady of the Lake.</note> too Nymphes waiting vppon her, arrayed all in ſylks attending her highneſſ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: from the midſt of the Pool, whear, vpon a moouabl Iland, bright blazing with torches, ſhe floting to land, met her Maieſty with a well penned meter and matter after this ſort: firſt of the auncientée of the Caſtl, whoo had been ownerz of the ſame éen till this day, moſt allweyz in the hands of the Earls of Leyceter, hoow ſhée had kept this Lake ſins king Arthurz dayz, and now vnderſtanding of her highneſſ hither cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, thought it both office and duetie in humbl wize to diſcouer her and her eſtate: offering vp the ſame, her Lake and poour therein, with promiſe of repayre vnto the Coourt. It pleazed her highneſſ too thank this Lady, &amp; too ad withall, we had thought indéed the Lake had been oours, and doo you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8645:7"/>
call it yourz noow? Wel we will héerin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon more with yoo héerafter.</p>
            <p>This Pageaunt waz clozd vp with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable harmony of Hautboiz, Shalmz, Corners, and ſuch oother looud muzik, that held on while her Maieſtie, pleazauntly ſo paſſed from thence toward the Caſtl gate: whearunto from the baſe Coourt ouer a dry valley caſt into a good foorm, waz thear fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a fayre Bridge of a twentie foot wide, <note place="margin">The bridge.</note> and a ſeauenty foot long, graueld for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, railed on either part with ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſts on a ſide, that ſtood a twelue foot a ſunder, <note place="margin">Seauen pair of poſts.</note> thikned betweene with well proportioned Pillars turnd.</p>
            <p>Vpon the firſt payr of poſts were ſet, too cumly ſquare wyre cagez, each a thrée foot long, too foot wide and hy: in them, liue Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Curluz, Shoouelarz, Hearſheawz, Godwitz, and ſuch like deinty Byrds of the <note place="margin">Syluanus prezents.</note> prezents of <hi>Syluanus</hi> the God of foul.</p>
            <p>On the ſecond payr, too great Syluerd Bollz, featly apted too the purpoze, filde with Applz, Pearz, Cherriz, Filberdz, Walnuts freſh vpon their brauuchez, and with Oringes, Poungarnets, Lemmanz, and Pipinz, all for the giftz of <hi>Pomona,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pomona.</note> Goddes of fruiez.</p>
            <p>The third pair of poſts, in too ſuch ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8645:8"/>
Bollz, had (all in earz, gréen and old) Wheat, Barly, Ootz, Beanz and Peaz, az the gifts of <hi>Ceres.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ceres.</hi> 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Poſt on the leaft hand, in a like ſyluered Boll, had Grapes in Cluſters whyte and red, gracified with their Vine leauez: the match poſt againſt it, had a payr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of great whyte ſyluer lyuery Pots for wyne: and before them two glaſſez of good capacitie filld full: the ton with whyte Wine, the two other with claret: ſo freſh of coolor, and of looke ſo louely ſmiling to the eyz of many, that by my feith mee thought by their léering, they could haue foound in their harts (az the euening was hot) to haue kiſt them ſwéetlie and thought it no ſin: and théez for the potencial prezents of <hi>Bacchus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bacchus.</hi> 4.</note> the God of wine.</p>
            <p>The fift payr had, each a fair large trey ſtreawd a littl with freſh graſſ, and in them, Coonger, Burt, Mullet, freſh Herring, Oi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Samon, Creuis, and ſuch like from <hi>Neptunus,</hi> God of the Sea. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neptunus.</hi> 5</note>
            </p>
            <p>On the ſixth payr of Poſts wear ſet two ragged ſtauez of ſyluer, as my Lord giuez them in armz, beautifully glittering of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour thereupon depending, Bowz, Arroz, Spearz, Shéeld, Head pées, Gorget, Corſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8645:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
lets, Swoords, Targets, and ſuch like for <hi>Mars</hi> gifts the God of war. And the apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyer <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mars.</hi> 6.</note> (me thought) waz it that thooz ragged ſtaues ſupported théez Martiall prezents, as well becauz théez Staues by their tines ſéem naturallie méete for the bearing of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moour, as alſo that they chiefly in this place might take vpon them principall protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her highnes Parſon, that ſo benignly pleazed her to take herbour.</p>
            <p>On the ſeauenth Poſts, the laſt and next too the Caſtl, wear thear pight, too fayr Bay braunchez of a fourfoot hy, adourned on all ſides with Lutes, Viollz, Shallmz, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, Flutes, Recorders and Harpes, as the prezents of <hi>Phoebus</hi> the God of Muzik <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phoebus.</hi> 7.</note> for reioyſing the mind, and alſo of Phizik, for health to the body.</p>
            <p>Ouer the Caſtl gate was there faſtened a Tabl beautifully garniſht abooue with her highneſſ armes, and featlie with Iuy wreathz b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ordred aboout: of a ten foot ſquare: the ground blak, whearupon in large white Capitall Roman fayr written: a Poem mencioning théez Gods and their giftes thus prezented vntoo her highneſſ: which, becauz it remained vnremooued, at leyzure &amp; pleaz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I took it oout, as foloeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8645:9"/>
                        <head>AD MAIESTATEM REGIAM.</head>
                        <l>Iupiter huc certos cernens TE tendere greſſus,</l>
                        <l>Coelicolas PRINCEPS actutum conuocat omnes:</l>
                        <l>Obſeqvium praestare iubet TIBI quen<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> benignum.</l>
                        <l>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde ſuas Syluanus aues, Pomona<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> fructus,</l>
                        <l>Alma Ceres fruges, hilarantia vina Liaeus,</l>
                        <l>Neptunus Piſces, tela &amp; tutantia Mauors,</l>
                        <l>Suaue melos Phoebus, ſolidam longam<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſalutem.</l>
                        <l>Dij TIBI REGINA haec (cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> SIS DIGNISSIMA) prebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</l>
                        <l>Haec TIBI cum Domino dedit ſe &amp; werda Kenelmi</l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>All the letterz that mention her Maieſty, which héer I put capitall, for reuerens and honor wear thear made in golld.</p>
            <p>But the night well ſpent, for that théez veriez by Torchlight, coold not eaſily bée read, by a Poet thearfore in a long cerule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oous garment, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſide and wide ſléeuez Venecian wize, drawen vp to his elboz, his Dooblet ſleeuez vnder that, Crimzen, nothing but ſilke: a Bay garland on hiz head, and a ſkro in his hand, making firſt an humble obeizaunz at her highneſſ cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, and pointing vntoo euerie prezent az hée ſpake: the ſame wear pronounced. Pleazauntly thus viewing the giftes az
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8645:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhe paſt, &amp; hoow the poſtsmight agrée with the ſpéech of the Poet, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> éend of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bridge &amp; entrée of the gate, waz her highnes recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a freſh delicate armony of Flutz, in perfourmauns of <hi>Phoebus</hi> prezents.</p>
            <p>So paſſing intoo the inner Coourt, her Maieſty (that neuer ridez but alone) thear ſet doun from her Pallfree, waz conueied vp to chamber: when after, did follo ſo great a peal of gunz, and ſuch lightning by fyre work a long ſpace toogither: as <hi>Iupiter</hi> woold ſheaw himſelf too bee no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther behind with hiz welcum, then the reſt of hiz Gods: and that woold hee haue all the countrie to kno: for indeed the noiz and flame wear h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard and ſéene a twenty myle of. Thus much Maſter Martin (that I remember me) for the firſt daiz <hi>Bien venu.</hi> Be yée not wery, for I am ſkant in the midſt of my matter.</p>
            <p>On ſunday: the forenoon occupied (az <note place="margin">Sunday.</note> for the Sabot day) in quiet and vacation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woork, &amp; in diuine ſeruis &amp; preaching at the pariſh church: The afternoon in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celent muzik, of ſundry ſwet inſtruments and in dauncing of Lordes &amp; Ladiez, and oother woorſhipfull degrées, vttered with ſuch liuely agilitee &amp; commendabl grace:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8645:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
az whither it moought be more ſtraunge too the eye, or pleazunt too the minde, for my part indéed I coold not diſcern: but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedingly well waz it (me thought) in both.</p>
            <p>At night late, az though <hi>Iupiter</hi> the laſt night, had forgot for bizineſſ, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born for curtezy &amp; quiet, part of hiz well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coom vntoo her highneſſ appointed: noow entring at the fyrſt intoo hiz purpoze mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly (az mortallz doo) with a warning pée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or too, proceding on with encres, at laſt the Alticonant diſpl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>az me hiz mayn poour: with blaz of burning darts, flying too &amp; fro, leamz of ſtarz coruſcant, ſtreamz and hail of firie ſparkes, lightninges of wildfier a water and lond, flight &amp; ſhoot of thunderboltz: al with ſuch countinauns, terror and vehemencie: that the heauins thundred, the waters ſoourged, the earth ſhooke: and in ſuch ſort ſurly, az had we not bee aſſured of the fulmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant deitée waz all hot in amitée, and could not otherwize wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hiz welcomming vnto her highneſſe: it woold haue made mee for my part, az hardy az I am, very veangeably afeard. This a doo laſted while h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> midnight waz paſt, that well waz mee ſoon after when I waz cought in my Cabayn. And thiz for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8645:10"/>
the ſecund day.</p>
            <p>Munday waz hot, and thearfore her <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Munday.</hi> 3.</note> highneſſe kept in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> till a fiue a clok in the éeuening: what time it pleazzd her too ryde foorth into the Chaſe too hunt the Hart of fors: which foound anon, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſore chaſed, and chafed by the hot <note place="margin">The hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of the Hare of fors.</note> purſuit of the hooundes, waz fain of fine fors, at laſt to take ſoil. Thear to beholld the ſwift fléeting of the Déer afore with the ſtately cariage of hiz head in hiz ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, ſpred (for the quantitée) lyke the ſail of a ſhip: the hoounds harroing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, az they had bin a number of ſkiphs too the ſpoyle of a karuell: the ton no leſſe eager in purchaz of hiz pray, then waz the the other earneſt in ſauegard of hiz life: ſo az the earning of the hoounds in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auns of their crie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwiftnes of the Déer, the running of footmen, the galloping of horſez, the blaſting of hornz, the halloing &amp; hewing of the huntſmen, with the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Echoz between whilez from the woods and waters in valleiz reſonnding, mooued pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime delectabl in ſo hy a degrée, az for ony parſon to take pleazure by mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſenſez at onez, in mine opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thear can be none ony wey comparable to this: And ſpeciall in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8645:11"/>
this place that of nature iz foormed ſo féet for the purpoſe in feith Maſter Martin if ye coold with a wiſh I woold ye had been at it: Wel the Hart waz kild, a goodly Déer, but ſo ceaſt not the game yet.</p>
            <p>For aboout nien a clock at the hither part of the Chaſe, whear torchlight atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: oout of the woods in her Maieſtiez return, rooughly came thear foorth <hi>Hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The ſauage man.</note> 
               <hi>Saluagio,</hi> with an Oken plant pluct vp by the roots in hiz hande, himſelf for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grone all in moſſ and Iuy: who, for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, geſture, and veterauns beſide, coountenaunſt the matter too very good liking, and had ſpeech to effect: That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſo long in theez wilde waſtes, whearin oft had he fared both far and néer, yet hapt hée neuer to ſee ſo glorioous an aſſemble afore: and noow caſt intoo great grief of mind, for that neyther by himſelf coold hee geſſ, nor knew whear elſe to bee taught, what they ſhould be, or whoo bare eſtate. Reports ſum had he hard of many ſtraunge thinges, but brooyled thearby ſo mooch the more in deſire of knoledge. Thus in great pangz bethought he &amp; cald he vpon all his familiarz &amp; companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>z: the Fawnz, the Satyres, the Nymphs, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8645:11"/>
Drya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des, &amp; the Hamadryades, but none making aunſwear, whearby hiz care the more encreaſing, in vtter grief &amp; extréem refuge calld hee allowd at laſt after hiz olld freend Echo that he wiſt would hyde nothing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, but tel him all if ſhe wear heer. Héer (quoth Echo.) Héer, Echo and <note place="margin">Echo.</note> art thou thear? (ſayz he) Ah hoow mooch haſt thou relieued my carefull ſpirits with thy curtezy onward. A my good Echo hér iz a marueiloouz prezenz of dignitée, what are they I pray thée, who iz Souerain, tell me I beſéech thee, or elz hoow moought I kno? I kno (quoth ſhee). Knoeſt thou ſayz hee; Mary that iz exceedingly well: why then, I dezire thée hartily to ſho mée what Maieſtie (for no mean degrée iz it) haue wee héer: a King or a Quéen? A Queen (quoth Echo.) A Quéen ſayez hee? Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly viewing a while, noow full certeynlie ſeemez thy tale to be true. And procéeding by this maner of dialog with an earneſt beholding her highnes a while, recounts he firſt hoow iuſtly that fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmer report<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agrée with hiz preſent ſight: toou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the beautifull linaments of coounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauns, the cumly proportion of body, the prinſly grace of prezenz, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graciouz giftz
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8645:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of nature with the rare and ſingular qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of both body and mind in her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty comoynd, and ſo apparant a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ey. Then ſhortly rehearſing Saterdaiz acts: of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bils ſalutation, of the Porters propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of hiz Trumpetoours muzik, of the Lake ladiez oration, of the ſeauen Gods ſeauen prezents: hee reporteth the incredibl ioy that all eſtatez in the land haue allweyz of her highnes whear ſo euer it cums: éen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with preſage and prayer of perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all felicitée, and with humbl ſubiection of him and hizzen &amp; all that they may do. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſort the matter went with littl dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferens I geſſe, ſauing only in this point: that the thing which héer I report in vnpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſht proez, waz thear pronounced in good méeter and matter, very wel indighted in rime. Echo finely framed moſt aptly by anſwerz thus to vtter all. And I ſhall tell yoo maſter Martin by the maſſ of a mad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture? az thiz Sauage for the more ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brake hiz trée a ſunder, keſt the top from him, it had allmoſt light vpon her highnes hors he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d: whereat he ſtartld and the gentlman mooch diſmayd, Sée the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitée of the Prins, az the foot men lookt well too the hors, and hee of Generoſitée
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8645:12"/>
ſoon callmd of him ſelf, no hurt no hurt quoth her highnes. Which words I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis yoo wee wear all glad to héer, &amp; cook them too be the beſt part of the play.</p>
            <p>Tuiſday, pleazaunt paſſing of the time <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tuiſday.</hi> 4.</note> with muzik &amp; daunſyng: ſauing that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward night it liked her Maieſty too walk a foot into the Chaſe ouer the Bridge: whear it pleaſed her to ſtand, while vpon the Pool oout of a Barge fine appoynted for the purpoze, too heer ſundry kinds of very delectabl Muzik. Thus recreated &amp; after ſum wallk her highnes returned.</p>
            <p>Wednſday, her Maieſty rode intoo the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wednſ.</hi> 5.</note> chaſe a hunting again of the hart of fors. The Deer after hiz property for refuge took the ſoyl: but ſo maſterd by hot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit on al parts that he was taken quik in the pool: the waterme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> held him vp hard by the hed, while at her highnes commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <note place="margin">The Hart pardoned.</note> he loſt hiz earz for a raundſum and ſo had pardon of lyfe.</p>
            <p>Thurſday, the foourteenth of this Iuly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thurſday.</hi> 6</note> and the ſyxth day of her Maieſtyez cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: a great ſort of ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dogs w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear thear tyed in the vtter Coourt, and thyrteen bearz in the inner. Whooſoeuer made the <note place="margin">A queaſt of Bearz.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>annell, thear wear inoow for a Queaſt &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8645:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
one for challenge &amp; néed we ar. A wight of great wizdoom and grauitée ſéemed their forman to be, had it cum to a Iury: But it fell oout that they wear cauzd too ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peer thear vpon no ſuch matter, but onlie too aunſwear too an auncient quarrell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéen them and the bandogs, in a cauſe of controuerſy that hath long depended, béen obſtinatly full often debated with ſharp and byting arguments a both ſydes, and coold neuer bee decided: grown noow too ſo marueyloous a mallys, that with ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obrayds and vncharitabl chaffings al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weiz they freat, az far az any whear the ton can héer, ſee, or ſmell the toother: and indeed at vtter deadly fohod. Many a maymd member, (God wot) blody face &amp; a torn cote hath the quarrell coſt betwéene them, ſo far likely the leſſe yet noow too be appeazd, az thear wants not partakerz too bak them a both ſidez.</p>
            <p>Well ſyr, the Bearz wear brought foorth intoo the Coourt, the Dogs ſet too them, too argu the points eeuen face too face, they had learnd coounſell allſo a both parts: what may they be coounted parciall that are retaind but a to ſyde? I wéen no. Very féers both ton and toother &amp;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8645:13"/>
eager in argument if the dog in pleadyng woold pluk the bear by the throte, the bear with trauers woould claw him again by the ſkaip, confeſſ &amp; a liſt, but a voyd a coold not that waz bound too the bar: and hiz coounſell tolld him that it coold bee too him no pollecy in pleading.</p>
            <p>Thearfore thus with fending &amp; proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, with plucking &amp; tugging, ſkratting &amp; byting, by plain tooth &amp; nayll a to ſide &amp; toother ſuch exſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of blood &amp; leather waz thear between them, az a moonths licking I wéen wyl not recoouer: and yet remain az far oout az euer they wear.</p>
            <p>It waz a ſport very pleazaunt of théez beaſtz: to ſée the bear with hiz pink nyez léering after hiz enmiez approch, the nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blneſſ &amp; wayt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dog too take hiz auaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and the fors &amp; experiens of the bear agayn to auoyd the aſſauts: if he wear bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in one place, hoow he woold pynch in an oother too get frée: that if he wear ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken onez, then what ſhyft with byting with clawyng, with roring toſſing &amp; tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling he woold woork too wynde hym ſelf from them: and when he waz loſe, to ſhake hiz earz twyſe or thryſe wyth the blud &amp; the ſlauer aboout hiz fiznamy, waz
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8645:14"/>
a matter of a goodly reléef.</p>
            <p>Az this ſport waz had a day time in the <note place="margin">Gunshot &amp; fyrework.</note> Caſtl, ſo waz thear abrode at night very ſtraunge and ſundry kindez of fier works, compeld by cunning too fly too and fro and too moount very hy intoo the ay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpward, and allſo too burn vnquenſhabl in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beneath: contrary yee wot, too fyerz, kinde. This intermingld with a great peal of guns: which all gaue, both too the ear and to the ey the greater grace and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, for that with ſuch order and art they wear tempered toouching time and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuauns, that waz about too houres ſpace.</p>
            <p>Noow within allſo in the mean time <note place="margin">Tumbling of the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</note> waz thear ſheawed before her highnes, by an Italian, ſuch feats of agilitice, in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, turninges, tumblinges, caſtinges, hops, iumps, leaps, ſkips, ſprings, gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſoomerſauts, caprettiez and flights: forward, backward, ſyde wize, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, vpward, and with ſundry windings gyrings and circumflexions: allſo lightly and with ſuch eaſines, az by mee in feaw words it iz not expreſſibl by pen or ſpeech I tell yoo plain. I bleaſt me by my faith to behold him, and began to doout whither a waz a man or a ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rite, and I wéen had
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8645:14"/>
doouted mée till this day: had it not been that anon I bethought me of men that can reazon &amp; talk with too toongs, and with too parſons at onez, ſing like burds, curteiz of behauiour, of body ſtrong and in ioynts ſo nymbl withall, that their bonez ſéem az lythie and plyaunt az ſyneuz. They dwel in a happy Iland (az the booke tearmz it) four moonths ſayling Southward beyond Ethiop.</p>
            <p>Nay Maſter Martin I tell you no ieſt: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diodor. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul. De anti. Egyptioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. lib.</hi> 3.</note> for both <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> an auncient Greeke hiſtoriographer in his third book of the acts of the olld Egypcians: and alſo from him, <hi>Conrad Geſnerus</hi> a great lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned man, and a very diligent writer in all good arguments of oour time (but decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) in the firſt Chapter of hiz <hi>Mithrida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mithrid. Geſneri.</note> reporteth the ſame. Az for thiz fellow I cannot tell what too make of him, ſaue that I may geſſe hiz bak be metalld like a Lamprey that haz no bone but a lyne like to a Lute ſtring.</p>
            <p>Wel ſyr let him paſſe and hiz featz, and this dayz paſtime withall, for héer iz az mooch az I can remember mee for Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiz entertainment.</p>
            <p>Friday and Saterday wear thear no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <note place="margin">Friday.</note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:8645:15"/>
ſheawz abrode, becauz the weather <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saterday.</hi> 8.</note> enclynde too ſum moyſter &amp; wynde: that very ſeazonably temperd the drought and the heat, cauzed by the continuans of fayr weather &amp; ſunſhyne afore, all the whyle ſyns her Maieſtiez thither cumming.</p>
            <p>A Sunday opportunely the weather <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sunday.</hi> 9.</note> brake vp again, and after diuine ſeruis in the pariſh church for the ſabot day, and a frutefull ſermon thear in the forenoon: at after noon in woorſhip of this kenel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorth Caſtl, and of God &amp; ſaint kenelm, whooz day forſooth by the calendar, this waz: a ſolem brydeale of a proper coopl <note place="margin">Brideale.</note> waz appointed: ſet in order in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyltyard, too cum and make thear ſheaw before the Caſtl in the great coourt, whear az waz pight a cumly quintine for featz at armz which when they had don, too march oout: at the northgate of the Caſtl homeward againe intoo the tooun.</p>
            <p>And thus were they marſhalld. Fyrſt, all the luſtie lads and bolld bachelarz of the pariſh, ſutablie euery wight with hiz blu buckeram bridelace vpon a braunch of green broom (cauz rozemary iz ſkant thear) tyed on hiz leaft arme (for a that ſyde lyez the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art) and hiz allder poll
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8645:15"/>
for a ſpear in hiz right hand, in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall order raunged on a fore, too &amp; too in a rank: ſum with a hat, ſum in a cap, ſum a cote ſum a ierken, ſum for lightnes in hiz dooblet &amp; hiz hoze, clean truſt with a point afore: ſum botes &amp; no ſpurz, he ſpurz &amp; no boots, and he neyther nother: one a ſadel, anoother a pad or a pannell faſtened with a cord, for gyrts wear geazon: and théez too the number of a ſixtéen wight ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding men and well beſéen: but the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom formoſt, in hiz fatherz tawny wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted iacket, (for his fréends wear fayn that he ſhoold be a brydegroom before the Quéen) a fayr ſtrawn hat with a capitall crooun ſtéepl wyze on hiz hed: a payr of harueſt glouez on hiz hands, az a ſign of good huſbandry: a pen &amp; inkorn at his bak. for he woold be knowen to be bookiſh lame of a leg that in his yooth was broken at football: well beloued yet of hiz mother that lent him a nu mufflar for a napkin that was tyed too hiz gyrdl for lozyng: It was no ſmall ſport too marke this minio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hiz full apointment, that throogh good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>coolation becam az formall in his action az had he béen a bridegroom indéed: with this ſpeciall grace by the wey, that euer az
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8645:16"/>
he woold haue framed him the better coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenauns, with the woors face he looke.</p>
            <p>Well ſyr, after théez horſmen, a liuely moriſoauns, according too the auncient manner, ſix daunſerz, Mawdmarion, and the fool. Then, thrée prety puzels az bright az a breaſt of bacon, of a thirtie yéere old a pées, that carried thrée ſpeciall ſpiſecakes of a buſhell of wheat, (they had it by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure oout of my Lords backhouſe,) before the Bryde: Syzely with ſet countenauns, and lips ſo demurely ſimpring, az it had béen a Mare cropping of a thiſtl. After théez a loouely loober woorts, freklfaced, red headed, cléen truſt in his dooblet &amp; hiz hoze taken vp now in déed by commiſſion, for that hee waz ſo loth to cum forward, for reuerens belike of hiz nu cut canuas doob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let: &amp; woold by hiz good will haue been but a gazer, but found too bée a meet actor for hiz offis: that waz to beare the bridecup, foormed of a ſweet ſucket barrell, a faire turnd foot ſet too it, all ſeemly be ſyluerd and parcell gilt, adourned with a beatiful braunch of broom, gayly begilded for roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary: from which, too brode brydelaces of red and yelloo buckeram begilded, and galauntly ſtreaming by ſuch wind az thear
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8645:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
waz (for hée carried it aloft:) This genet cupbearer, yet had hiz freckld fiznemy ſumwhat vnhappily infeſted az hee went by the byzy flyez, that floct about the bride cup for the ſwéetnes of the ſucket that it ſauored on: but hée like a tall fello, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood their mallis ſtoutly (ſée what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood may do) bet them away, kild them by ſcores, ſtood to hiz charge and marched on in good order.</p>
            <p>Then folloed the worſhipfull Bride, led (after the cuntrie maner) betwéen too aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient pariſhionerz, honeſt toounſmen. But a ſtale ſtallion and a wel ſpred, (hot az the weather waz) God wot, and an il ſmelling waz ſhe: a thirtie yéer old, of colour broun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, not very beautifull in déed but vgly fooul ill fauord: yet marueyloous fain of the offis, becauſe ſhee hard ſay ſhee ſhoold dauns before the Quéen, in which feat ſhée thought ſhee woold foote it az finely az the beſt: Well, after this bride cam thear by too and too, a dozen damzels for bridemaides: that for fauor, attyre, for facion and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines: were az méete for ſuch a bride az a tréen ladl for a porige pot: mo, but for fear of carring all clean had béen appointed: but theez feaw wear inoow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:8645:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Az the cumpany in this order wear cum into y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> coourt, maruelous wear the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall acts that wear doon thear that day.</p>
            <p>The Brydegroome for preeminens <note place="margin">Running at Quintine.</note> had the fyrſt coors at the Quintyne, brake hiz ſpear <hi>treshardiment:</hi> but his mare in hiz manage did a littl ſo titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. that mooch a doo had hiz manhod to ſit in his ſadl, &amp; too ſcape the foyl of a fall: with the help of his band yet he recoouerd himſelf, and loſt not hiz ſtyrops (for he had none too his ſaddl): had no hurt as it hapt, but only that hiz gyrt burſt, and loſt hiz pen &amp; inkorn that he waz redy to wep for. But hiz handkercher, az good hap waz, found he ſafe at his gyrdl: that chéerd him ſumwhat, &amp; had good regard it ſhoold not be fyeld. For though heat &amp; coolnes vpon ſundry occazions made him ſumtime too ſweat, and ſumtime eumatick: yet durſt he be bollder too blo hiz noze &amp; wype hiz face with the flapet of his fatherz iacket, then with hiz mothers mufflar. tiz a goodly matter, when yooth iz manerly brought vp in fatherly looue &amp; motherly aw.</p>
            <p>Noow ſyr, after the Brydegroom had made hiz coors, ran the reſt of the band a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8645:17"/>
whyle in ſum order, but ſoon after, tag and rag, cut &amp; long tail: whear the ſpecialty of the ſport waz, to ſee: how ſum for hiz ſlakneſſ had a good bob with the bag, and ſum for his haſte too toppl dooun right, &amp; cum tumbling to the poſt: ſum ſtryuing ſo mooch at the firſt ſetting oout, that it ſéemd a queſtion betwéene the man &amp; the beaſt, whither the coors ſhoold be made a horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back or a foot: and put foorth with the ſpurz, then wold run hiz race byas among the thickeſt of the throng, that dooun came they toogyther hand ouer hed: anoother, whyle he directed hiz coors to the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne, hiz iument woold cary him too a mare amoong the pepl: ſo hiz hors az a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moroos, az him ſelfe aduenturoous. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, too run &amp; miſſ the quintyne with hiz ſtaff, and hit the boord with his hed.</p>
            <p>Many ſuch gay gamez wear thear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong théez ryderz: who by &amp; by after, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a greater coorage leaft thear quintining, and ran one at anoother. Thear to ſée the ſtearn countenauns, the grym looks, the cooragioous attempts, the deſperat adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turez, the daungeroous coor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſez, the féers encoounterz, whearby the buff at the man, and the coounterbuff at the hors, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8645:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
both ſumtime cam topling to the ground. By my tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th Maſter Martyn twaz a liuely paſtime, I beléeue it woold haue mooued ſum man too a right méery mood, thoogh had it be toold him hiz wife lay a dying.</p>
            <p>And héertoo folloed az good a ſport (me <note place="margin">Hok Tuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day by the Couentree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men.</note> thooght) prezented in an hiſtoricall ku, by certain good harted men of Couentrée, my Lordes neighboors thear: who vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding amoong them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing that coold not bee hidden from ony: hoow carefull and ſtudious hiz honor waz, that by all pleazaunt recreaſions her highnes might beſt fynd her ſelf wellcom, and bee made gladſum and mery (the groundworke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede and foundacion of hiz Lordſhips myrth and gladneſſe of vs all) made peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they moought renu noow their olld ſtoriall ſheaw: Of argument how the Danez whylom héere in a troubloous ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Florileg. li.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 300.</note> wear for quietneſſe born withall &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feard in peas, that anon by outrage &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portabl inſolency, abuzing both <hi>Ethelred</hi> the king then and all eſtates euerie whear byſide: at the greuoous complaint &amp; cooun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Huna the kings chieftain in warz, on Saint Brices night. <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1012.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8645:18"/>
(Az the book ſayz) that falleth yéerely on the thirtéenth of Nouember) wear all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht and the Ream rid. And for becauz the matter mencioneth how valiantly our Engliſh women for looue of their cuntrée behaued themſeluez: expreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in actionz &amp; rymez after their maner, they thought it moought mooue ſum myrth to her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie the rather.</p>
            <p>The thing ſaid they iz grounded on ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and for paſtime woont too bee plaid in oour Citee yéerely: without ill exampl of mannerz, papiſtry, or ony ſuperſtition: and els did ſo occupy the heads of a number, that likely inoough woold haue had woorz meditationz: had an auncient beginning and a long continuauns: tyll noow of late laid dooun, they knu no cauz why onleſſ it wear by the zeal of certain theyr Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherz: men very commendabl for their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour and learning, &amp; ſwéet in their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but ſumwhat too ſour in preaching awey theyr paſtime: wiſht therefore, that az they ſhoold continu their good doctrine in pulpet, ſo, for matters of pollicy &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernauns of the Citie, they woold permit them to the Mair and Magiſtratez: and ſey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by my feyth, Maſter Martyn, they
<pb facs="tcp:8645:19"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 lines">
                  <desc>〈6 lines〉</desc>
               </gap>,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by profeſſion a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and that right ſkilfull, very cunning in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ens, and hardy az Gawin, for hiz ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſword hangs at his tablz éend: great ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight hath he in matters of ſtorie: For az for king Arthurz book, Huo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Burdeaus, The foour ſuns of Aymon, Beuys of Hampton, The ſquyre of lo degree, The knight of courteſy, and the Lady Faguell, Frederik of Gene, Syr Eglamoour, Sir Tryamoour, Syr Lamwell, Syr Iſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras, Syr Gawyn, Olyuer of the Caſtl, Lucres and Eurialus, Virgils life, The caſtl of Ladiez. The wido Edyth, The King &amp; the Tanner. Frier Rous, Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas, Gargantua, Robinhood, Adambel, Clim of the clough &amp; Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cloudeſley, The Churl &amp; the Burd, The ſeauen wiſe Maſters, The wife lapt in a Morels ſkin. The ſak full of nuez. The ſeargeaunt that became a Fryar, Skogan, Collyn cloout. The Fryar &amp; the boy, Elynor Rumming, and the Nutbrooun maid, with many moe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8645:19"/>
then I rehearz héere: I beléeue hee haue them all at hiz fingers endz.</p>
            <p>Then in Philoſophy both morall &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, I think he be az naturally ouerſéen: beſide poetrie and Aſtronomie, and oother hid ſciencez, as I may geſſe by the omber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of hiz books: whearof part az I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the Sheperdz kalender. The Ship of Foolz, Danielz dreamz, the booke of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, <hi>Stans puer ad menſam,</hi> the hy wey to the Spitlhouſe, Iulian of Brainfords teſtament, the caſtle of Loue, the booget of Demaunds, the hundred Mery talez, the book of Riddels, the Seauen ſororz of we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the prooud wiues Pater noſter, the Chapman of a peniwoorth of Wit: Beſide hiz auncient playz. Yooth &amp; charitée, Hik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkorner, Nugize, Impacient pouerty, and héerwith doctor Boords breuiary of health. What ſhoold I rehearz héer, what a bunch of ballets &amp; ſongs all auncient: Az Broom broom on hil. So wo iz me begon, troly lo. Ouer a whinny Meg. Hey ding a ding. Bony laſſ vpon a gréen. My bony on gaue me a bek. By a bank az I lay: and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred more, he hath fair wrapt vp in Parch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and bound with a whipcord.</p>
            <p>And az for Allmanaks of antiquitée, (a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8645:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
point for Ephemerides) I wéene hee can ſheaw from Iaſper Laet of An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>warp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Noſtradam of Frauns, and thens vnto oour Iohn Securiz of Salſbury. To ſtay ye no longer héerin I dare ſay hee hath az fair a library for théez ſciencez, &amp; az many goodly monuments both in proze &amp; poetry &amp; at afternoonz can talk az much without book, az ony Inholder betwixt Brainford and Bagſhot, what degree ſoeuer he be.</p>
            <p>Beſide thiz in the field a good Marſhall at muſters: of very great credite &amp; truſt in the toun héer, for he haz béen choze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Alecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner many a yéere, when hiz betterz haue ſtond by: &amp; euer quited himſelf with ſuch eſtimation, az yet too the taſt of a cup of Nippitate, hiz iudgement will be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the beſt in the pariſh, be hiz noze near ſo re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d.</p>
            <p>Captain Cox cam marching on valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before, cléen truſt &amp; gartered aboue the knée, all freſh in a veluet cap (maſter Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lent it him) flooriſhing with hiz ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwoord, and another fenſmaſter with him: thus in the foreward making room for the reſt. After the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proudly prickt on formoſt, the daniſh launſknights on horſbak, and then the Engliſh: each with their allder
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8645:20"/>
poll martially in their hand. Eeuen at the <note place="margin">The couen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree play.</note> firſt entrée the méeting waxt ſumwhat warm: that by and by kindled with corage a both ſidez, gru from a hot ſkirmiſh vnto a blazing battail: firſt by ſpeare and ſhield, outragious in their racez az ramz at their rut, with furious encoounterz that togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they tumbl too the duſt, ſumtime hors and man: and after fall too it with ſworde &amp; target, good bangz a both ſidez: the fight ſo ceaſſing, but the battail not ſo ended, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loed the footmen, both the hoſtez ton after toother: firſt marching in ranks: then war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik turning, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ranks into ſquadrons, then in too trianglz fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that intoo rings, &amp; ſo winding oout again: A valiant captain of great prowez az fiers az a fox aſſauting a gooz, waz ſo hardy to giue the firſt ſtroke: then get they griſly togyther: that great waz the actiuitée that day too be ſéen thear a both ſidez: ton very eager for purchaz of pray, toother vtterly ſtoout for redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of libertie: thus, quarrell enflamed fury a both ſidez. Twiſe the Danes had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but at the laſt conflict, beaten doun, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercom and many led captiue for triumph by our Engliſh wéemen.</p>
            <p>This waz the effect of this ſheaw, that
<pb facs="tcp:8645:21"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and vnrulines of the people, waz cauz that this ſolemnitee of Brideale, &amp; daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing had not the full muſter waz hoped for: and but a littl of the Couentrée ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her highnes alſo ſaw: commaunded thear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on the Tuiſday folloing to haue it ful oout: az accordingly it waz prezented, whearat her Maieſtie laught well: they wear the iocunder, and ſo mooch the more becauz her highnes had giuen them too buckes and fiue marke in mony to make mery togyther: they prayed for her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, long, happily to reign &amp; oft to cum thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that oft they moought ſée héer: &amp; what, reioycing vpon their ampl reward, and what, triumphing vpon the good accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauns: they vaunted their play waz neuer ſo dignified, nor euer any players afore ſo beatified.</p>
            <p>Thus though the day took an éend, yet
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8645:21"/>
ſlipt not the night all ſléeping awey: for az neyther offis nor obſequy ceaſſed at any tyme too the full, to perform the plot hiz honor had appoynted: So, after ſupper waz thear a play prezented of a very good theam, but ſo ſet foorth by the Actoourz wel handling that pleazure &amp; mirth made it ſeeme very ſhort, though it laſted too good oourz and more. But ſtay maſter Martyn all iz not doon yet.</p>
            <p>After the play oout of hand, folloed a moſt delicioouz and (if I may ſo terme it) an Ambroſiall Banket: whearof, whither I myght more muze at the deintyneſſe, ſhapez and the coſt: or els at the variete &amp; number of the diſſhez (that wear a thrée hundred) for my part I coold littl tel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and noow leſſ I aſſure yoo. Her maieſty eat ſmally or nothing: which vnderſtood, the coorſez wear not ſo orderly ſerued &amp; ſizely ſet dooun, but wear by and by az diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waſted &amp; coorſly conſumed, more court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly me thought then curteouſly. But that was no part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter, moought it pleaz and be liked &amp; do that it cam for, then waz all well inough.</p>
            <p>Vntoo this banket thear waz appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a maſk: for riches of aray, of an incre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dibl
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8645:22"/>
coſt: but the time ſo far ſpent and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry late in the night noow, waz cauz that it cam not foorth to the ſheaw. And thus for Sondayz ſeazon hauing ſtayd yoo the lenger (according too the matter) heer make I an eend: ye maye breath yee a while.</p>
            <p>Munday the eyghteenth of this Iuly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Munday.</hi> 10</note> the weather being hot, her highnes kept the Caſtl for coolneſſ, till aboout fiue a clok her Maieſty in the Chaſe, hunted the hart (az afore) of fors: that whyther wear it by the cunning of the huntſmen, or by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.</note> the naturall deſyre of the Deer, or els by both: anon he gat him too ſoyl agayne, which reyzed the accuſtomed delight: a paſtime indéede ſo intyrely pleazaunt, az whearof at times whoo may haue the ful and frée fruition, can find no more ſacietée (I wéen) for a recreation, then of theyr good v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aundes at timez for their ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Wéll, the game waz gotten, and her highnes returning: cam thear vppon a ſwimming Mermayd (that from top too tayl waz an eyghtéen foot long) <hi>Triton Neptunes</hi> blaſter: whoo, with hiz tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet foormed of a wrinkld wealk az her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8645:22"/>
waz in ſight, gaue ſoound very ſhrill &amp; ſonoroous, in ſign he had an ambaſſy too pronoouns<hi>:</hi> anon her highnes waz cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vpon the bridge whearunto he made hiz fiſh to ſwim the ſwifter, and he then declared: how the ſupreame ſalſipotent Monarch Neptune, the great God of the ſwelling ſeaz, Prius of profunditées, and Soouerain Segnior of al Lakez, freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waterz, Riuerz, Créekes, &amp; Goolphs: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding how a cruel Knight, one ſyr Bruſe ſauns pitée, a mortall enmy vntoo Ladiez of eſtate, had long lyen about the banks of this pooll in wayt with his ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds heer to diſtreſſ the Lady of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lake, whear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe hath béen reſtrayned not only from hauing any vſe of her ancient liberty and territoriez in théez parts: but alſo of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king repayr &amp; giuing atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dauns vnto yoo nobl Qnéen (qd. he) az ſhe woold, ſhee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, and allſo ſhoold: dooth thearfore ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify: and héerto, of yoo az of hiz good leag and déer fréend make this requeſt, that ye will deyn but too ſheaw yoor parſon tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard this pool, whearby yoor only prezens ſhall be matter ſufficient of abandoning this vucurteſſ knight, and putting all his bands too flight, &amp; alſo of deliuerauns of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8645:23"/>
the lady oout of this thralldom. Moouing héerwith from the bridge &amp; fléeting more intoo the pool, chargeth he in Neptunes name: both Colus with al his windez, the waters with hiz ſprings, hiz fyſh &amp; fooul, and all his clients in the ſame, that they ne be ſo hardye in any fors too ſtur, but kéep them calm &amp; quiet while this Quéen be prezent. At which petition her highnes ſtaying, it appeerd ſtraight hoow ſyr Bruſe became vnſéen, his bands ſkaled, and the Lady by and by, with her too Nymphs, floting vpon her moouable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands <hi>(Triton</hi> on hiz mermaid ſkimming by) approched toward her highnes on the bridge: az well too declare that her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiez prezens hath ſo graciouſlye thus wrought her deliuerauns, az allſo to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuze her not comming to coourt az ſhe promiſt, and chéefly to prezent her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty (az a token of her duty &amp; good hart) for her highneſſ recreation with thiz gift, which was <hi>Arion</hi> that excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; famouz Muzicien, in tyre &amp; appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtraunge well ſéeming too hiz parſon, ryding alofte vpon hiz olld fréend the Dolphin, (that from hed too tayl waz a foour &amp; twenty foot long) &amp; ſwymd hard by theez Ilands<hi>:</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:8645:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
héerwith <hi>Arion</hi> for theez great benefitez, after a feaw well coouched words vntoo her Maieſty of thanksgyuing, in ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame: béega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a delectabl ditty of a ſong wel apted too a melodious noiz, compoounded of ſix ſeuerall inſtruments al coouert, caſting ſoou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Dolphins belly within, <hi>Arion</hi> the ſeauenth ſitting thus ſinging (az I ſay) withoout.</p>
            <p>Noow ſyr, the ditty in miter ſo aptly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dighted to the matter, and after by voys ſo delicioouſly deliuerd: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſong by a ſkilful artiſt intoo hiz parts ſo ſwéetly ſorted: each part in hiz inſtrument ſo clean &amp; ſharpely toouched, euery inſtrument again in hiz kind ſo excellently tunabl: and this in the éeuing of the day, reſoounding from the callm waters: whear prezens of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty &amp; longing too liſten had vtterly dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped all noyz &amp; dyn: the hole armony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyd in tyme, tune, &amp; temper thus incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably melodious: with what pleazure (Maſter Martin) with what ſharpnes of conceyt, with what lyuely delighte this moought pears into the heerers harts: I pray ye imagin yoor ſelf az ye may, for ſo God iudge me, by all the wit &amp; cunning I haue, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not expreſſ, I promis yoo. <hi>Mais</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:8645:24"/>
               <hi>ieo bien vieu cela Monſeur, que fort gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de eſt la pouuoyr qu'auoit la treſnoble Science de Muſique ſur les eſprites humains.</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ye me? I haue told ye a great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noow. As for me ſurely I was lulld in ſuch liking &amp; ſo loth too leaue of, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mooch a doo a good while after, had I, to fynde me whear I waz. And take ye this by the way, that for the ſmal ſkyl in muzik, that God hath ſent me (ye kno it iz ſumwhat) ile ſet the more by my ſelf while my name iz Langham, and grace a God. A, muzik iz a nobl Art.</p>
            <p>A, ſtay a while, ſee a ſhort wit: by my trooth I had almoſt forgot. This daye waz a day of grace beſide, whearin wear auaunced fyue Gentlemen of woorſhippe vnto the degrée of knighthood, Sir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Cecyl, ſun &amp; heyr vntoo the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norabl <note place="margin">Knights made.</note> the Lord Treazorer, Syr Henry Cobham, broother vnto the Lord Cobha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Syr Thomas Stanhop, Syr Arthur Baſſet, and Syr Thomas Treſham: and allſo by her highnes accuſtumed mercy &amp; charitée, nyne cured of the peynfull and daungerous diſeaz, called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings euill, for that Kings &amp; Quéenz of this Realm, withoout oother medſin (ſaue only by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8645:24"/>
handling &amp; prayerz) only doo cure it: bear with me, though perchauns I place not thoz Gentlmen in my recitall héer, after theyr eſtatez: for I am neyther good he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raud of armez, nor yet kno hoow they are ſet in the Subſydy bookez. Men of great woorſhip I vnderſtand they are all.</p>
            <p>Tuiſday, according to commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tuiſday.</hi> 11</note> cam oour Couentrée men. what their matter waz, of her highnes myrth and good acceptauns, and rewarde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too them, and of their reioyſing thear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, I ſheawd you afore, and ſo ſay the leſſ noow.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday in the forenoon, preparaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wednſ.</hi> 12.</note> was in hand for her Maieſty too haue ſupt in Wedgeno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, a thrée myle weſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Caſtl. A goodly park of the Quéenz Maieſtyez: for that cauz, a fayr Paui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and other prouiſion accordingly thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent &amp; prepared: but by meanz of weather not ſo cléerly diſpozed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter waz countermaunded again. That had her highnes hapned this daye too haue cummen abrode: there was made reddy a deuiſe of Goddeſſez &amp; Nymphes: which az well for the ingenious argument, az for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wel handling of it in rime &amp; endigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8645:25"/>
woold vndooutedly haue gaind great lyking &amp; mooued no leſſ delight. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular itéez, whearof I ceas to entreat: leaſt like the boongling carpentar, by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting the péecez, I mar a good frame in the bad ſetting vp, or by my fond tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pring afore hand embleamiſh the beauty, when it ſhoold be reard vp in déede.</p>
            <p>A this day allſo waz thear ſuch earneſt tallk &amp; appoincment of remoouing that I gaue ouer my noting, and harkened after my hors.</p>
            <p>Mary ſyr I muſt tell yoo: Az all ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoour waz too mooue mirth &amp; paſtime (az I tolld ye): éeuen ſo a ridiculoous deuiſe of an auncient minſtrell, &amp; hiz ſong waz prepared to haue been profferd, if méete time &amp; place had béen foound for it. Ons in a woorſhipfull company, whear full ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, he recoounted his matter in ſort az it ſhoould haue been vttred, I chaunſed too be: what I noted, heer thus I tel yoo: A parſon very méet ſéemed he for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poze, of a xlv yéers olld apparelled part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he woold himſelf. Hiz cap of: his hed ſéemly roounded tonſter wyze: fayr kembd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with a ſpoonge deintly dipt in a littl ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons greaz was finely ſmoothed too make
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8645:25"/>
it ſhine like a Mallards wing. Hiz beare ſmugly ſhauen: and yet hiz ſhyrt after the nu tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, with ruffs fayr ſtarched, ſléeked, and gliſtering like a payr of nu ſhooz: mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalld in good order: wyth a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fetling ſtick, and ſtoout that euery ruff ſtood vp like a wafer: a ſide gooun of kendall green, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the freſhnes of the yéer noow, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at the neck with a narro gorget, faſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned afore with a white claſp and a kéepar cloſe vp to the chin: but eaſily for heat too vndoo when he liſt: Séemly begyrt in a red caddiz gyrdl: from that a payr of capped Sheffeld kniuez hanging a to ſide: Out of hiz bozome drawne foorth a lappet of his napkin, edged with a blu lace, &amp; marked with a trulooue, a hart, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a D. for Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian: for he was but a bachelar yet.</p>
            <p>Hiz gooun had ſyde ſleeuez dooun to midlegge, ſlit from the ſhooulder too the hand &amp; lined with white cotten. Hiz doob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſleeuez of blak woorſted, vpon them a a payr of poynets of tawny Chamblet la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a long the wreaſt wyth blu threeden points, a wealt toward the hand of fuſtian anapes: a payr of red neatherſtocks: a pair of pumps on hiz féet with a croſſ cut at the toze for cornz: not nu indéede, yet cleanly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8645:26"/>
blakt with ſoot, &amp; ſhining az a ſhoing horn.</p>
            <p>Aboout hiz nek a red rebon dſutable too hiz girdl: hiz harp in good grace depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunt before him: hiz wreaſt tyed to a gréen lace and hanging by: vnder the gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get of hiz gooun a fair flagon cheyn (pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, for ſiluer) az a ſquier minſtrel of Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilſex, that trauaild the cuntrée this ſoom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeazon vnto fairz &amp; worſhipfull mens hoouſez: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hiz chein hoong a Schoochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with mettall &amp; cooller reſplendant vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hiz breaſt of the auncient armez of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington: vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a queſtion whearof: he, az one that waz wel ſchoold, &amp; coold hiz leſſon par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit withoout booke too aunſwear at full, if queſtion wear aſkt hym, declared: hoow the woorſhipfull village of Iſtington in Middelſex, well knooen too bee one of the moſt auncient and beſt toounz in England next London at thiz day: for the feythfull fréendſhip of long time ſheawed az well at Cookez feaſt in Alderſgate ſtréete yeerely vpon holly Rood day, az allſo at all ſolem bridalez in the citie of London all the yéer after: in well ſeruing them of furmenty for porage, not ouerſod till it be too weak: of mylk for theyr flawnez, not pild nor chalked: of cream for their cuſtardes, not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8645:26"/>
frothed nor thykned with floour: and of butter for theyr paſtiez, and pyepaſt, not made of well curds, nor gatherd of whey in ſoommer: nor mingled in winter with ſalt butter watered or waſht, did obteyn long ago thez woorſhipfull armez in coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler &amp; foorm az yee ſée: which are the armz a field argent, as the field and groound in deed, whearin the milkwiuez of thiz woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy tooun, and euery man els in hys facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty doth trade for hiz liuing: on a Feſſ Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thrée platez betwéene thrée milke tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerds proper. The thrée milk tankerds, az the proper veſſell whearin the ſubſtauns, and matter of their trade iz too and fro tranſported. The Feſſ Tenny, which iz a cooler betokening dout &amp; ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo az ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>picion &amp; good heed taking, az wel to their markets &amp; ſeruants, az to their cuſtomers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they truſt not too farre: may bring vnto them platez, that iz coynnd ſyluer: thrée, that iz ſufficient and plentie, for ſo that number in Armory may well ſignifie.</p>
            <p>For Creaſt vpon a wad of ote ſtrawe for a wreath, a boll of furmenty: Wheat (az yee kno) iz the moſt precious gyft of <hi>Ceres,</hi> and in the midſt of it, ſticking a <note place="margin">The horn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpoonz.</note> doozen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hornſpoonz in a bunch az the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8645:27"/>
meeteſt too eate furmenty po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage wythall: a doozen, az a number of plenty compleat for full cheere or a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and of horn, az of a ſubſtauns more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimabl then iz made for a great deel: bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nether ſo churliſh in weight az iz met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall: nor ſo froward and brittl to manure, az ſtone, nor yet ſo ſoily in vſe nor roough to the lips az wood iz: but lyght, plyaunt, and ſmooth, that with a littl licking wooll allweiz be kept az clen az a dy. With yoor paciens Gentlmen (quoth the minſtrel) be it ſaid: wear it not in deede that hornz bee ſo plentie, hornware I beleeue woold bee more ſet by than it iz, and yet are thear in our parts that wyll not ſtick too auoow, that many an honeſt man both in citée and cuntrée hath had hiz hoous by horning well vphollden, and a daily fréend allſo at néed. And thiz with your fauoour may I further affirm: a very ingenioous parſon waz hée, that for dignitée of the ſtuff, coold thus by ſpooning deuiſe, to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uauns the horn ſo neer too the hed.</p>
            <p>With great congruens alſo wear théez hornſpoonz put too the wheat: az a token and porcion of <hi>Cornucopiae,</hi> the horn of <hi>Achelous,</hi> which the <hi>Naiades</hi> did fil with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ouid. met. lib.</hi> 9.</note>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:8645:27"/>
all good frutez, corn &amp; grain: &amp; after did conſecrate vnto abooundauns and plenty.</p>
            <p>This ſkoochion with beaſtz very aptly agréeing both to the armz and to the trade of the bearerz, glorioouſly ſupported, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéen a gray Mare (a beaſt meeteſt for carying of mylktankards) her pannell on her bak, az alwayz reddy for ſeruis at euery feaſt and brydale at neede, her tail ſplayd at moſt eaz: and her filly fole, fallo and a flaxen mane after the ſyre.</p>
            <p>In the ſkro vndergrauen (quoth hee) iz thear a proper woord, an <hi>hemiſtichi,</hi> well ſquaring with al the reſt, taken out of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerns</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Salern. ca.</note> chapter, of things that moſt nooriſh mans body: <hi>Lac, Caſeus infans.</hi> That iz good milke and yoong chéez. And thus mooch Gintlmen, and pleaz you (quoth he). for the armz of oour woorſhipfull tooun. And thearwithal made a manerly leg, and ſo held his peas.</p>
            <p>Az the cumpany pawzed and the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrell ſémde to gape after a praiz for hiz <hi>Beauparlar:</hi> and bicauz he had renderd hiz leſſon ſo well: Saiz a good fello of the cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, I am ſory to ſee hoow mooch the poore minſtrell miſtakez the matter: for indeed the armez are thus.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8645:28"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 lines">
                  <desc>〈6 lines〉</desc>
               </gap>
with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>king with her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for flyez, and her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying after the dam for ſuk. This woord La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Caſeus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fans. That is, a freſh cheez and cream, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon cry that theez milkwiuez make in London ſtréetes yéerly, betwixt Eaſter and whitſontide: and this iz the very mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I kno it well inough, and ſo ended hiz tale, and ſate him dooun again.</p>
            <p>Héerat euery man laught a good, ſaue the minſtrell: that thoogh the fooll wear made priuy, all waz but for ſport, yet too ſee him ſelf thus croſt with a contrary ku that hee lookt not for, woold ſtraight haue geen ouer all, waxt very wayward, eager and ſoour: hoow be it laſt by ſum entreaty &amp; many fayr woords, with ſak &amp; ſuger, we ſweetned him againe, and after becam az mery az a py. Appeerez then a freſh, in hiz ful formalitée with a louely loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k: after thrée loly coourſiez, cleered his vois with a hem and a reach, and ſpat oout withal, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8645:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hiz lips with the hollo of his hand, for fyling hiz napkin, temperd a ſtring or too with hiz wreaſt: and after a littl warh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on hiz harp for a prelude, came foorth with a ſollem ſong, warraunted for ſtory oout of king Aurthurz acts, the firſt booke <note place="margin">King Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thurs book.</note> and 26. chapter, whearof I gate a copy, and that iz this.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>SO it befell vpon a Penticoſt day,</l>
               <l>When king Arthur at Camelot kept coourt rial,</l>
               <l>With hiz cumly Quéen dame Gaynoour the gay.</l>
               <l>And many bolld Barrons ſitting in hall,</l>
               <l>Ladies apparaild in purpl and pall,</l>
               <l>When herauds in hukes herried full by</l>
               <l>Largeſſ Largeſſ cheualiers treſhardy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ A doouty Dwarf too the vppermoſt deas</l>
               <l>Right peartly gan prik and knéeling on knee,</l>
               <l>With ſteeuen full ſtoout amids all the preas,</l>
               <l>Said hail ſyr king, God thee ſaue and ſee,</l>
               <l>King Ryens of Northgalez gréeteth well thee,</l>
               <l>And bids that thy beard anon thou him ſend,</l>
               <l>Or els from thy iawz he will it of rend,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ For his robe of ſtate, a rich ſkarlet mantell,</l>
               <l>With a leauen kings beards bordred aboout,</l>
               <l>Hee hath made late, and yet in a cantell</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:8645:29"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="8 lines">
                     <desc>〈8 lines〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Lordz bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtampt, ſquirez ſtartld az ſtéedz in a ſtoour.</l>
               <l>Yeem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and pagez yeald <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>out in the hall,</l>
               <l>Thearwith cam in Syr Bay of Seueſhall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Syleus my ſuffrainz quoth the courteyz Knight,</l>
               <l>And in that ſtoound the chearm becam ſtill,</l>
               <l>The Dwarfs dynner full deerly waz dight,</l>
               <l>For wine and waſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell hée had at hiz will,</l>
               <l>And when hee had eaten and fed hiz fill.</l>
               <l>One hundred peeces of coyned gould,</l>
               <l>Wear giuen the Dwarfe for hiz meſſage bolld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Say too Syr Ryens thou Dwarf quoth the king,</l>
               <l>That for his proud meſſage I him defy,</l>
               <l>And ſhortly with baſinz and panz will him ring,</l>
               <l>Oout of Northgalez whearaz hée and I</l>
               <l>With ſweards and no razerz ſhall vtterly try,</l>
               <l>Which of vs both iz the better Barber:</l>
               <l>And thearwith he ſhook hiz ſword Excalaber.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8645:29"/>
At this, the minſtrell made a pauz &amp; a curt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zy, for <hi>Primus paſſus.</hi> More of the ſong iz thear, but I gat it not, Az for the matter had it cum to the ſheaw, I think the fello would haue handled it well y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noough.</p>
            <p>Her highnes tarryed at Kyllingwoorth tyll the wedneſday after, being the 27 of this Iuly, and the nintéenth <hi>(incluſiue)</hi> of her Maieſtiez cumming thither.</p>
            <p>For which ſeuen daiz, perceyuing my notez ſo ſlenderly aunſwering: I tooke it leſſ blame, too ceas &amp; thearof too write yoo nothing at al, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuch matterz to write nothing likely, And ſo mooch the rather (az I haue well betho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght me) that if I dyd but ruminate the dayz I haue ſpoken of, I ſhall bring oout yet ſumwhat more, méet for yoor appetite, (thoogh a deinty tooth haue ye) which I beleue yoor tender ſtomak will brook wel inoogh.</p>
            <p>Whearof part iz: fyrſt hoow according to her highnes name <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenz.</note> which I heer ſay oout of the Hebru ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth (amoong oother) the <hi>Seauenth of my God:</hi> diuerz things heer, did ſoo iuſtly in number ſquare with the ſame. Az fyrſt, her highnes hither cumming in this ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth
<pb facs="tcp:8645:30"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="8 lines">
                  <desc>〈8 lines〉</desc>
               </gap> vpon her coourt thear too make her Maieſty merry.</p>
            <p>Sage Saturn himſelf in parſon (that <note place="margin">Saturn and Pallas.</note> bycauz of hiz lame leg co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld not ſo well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ur) in chayr thearfore too take order with the graue officerz of hoouſhold, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in deed with the good aduiſe of his prudent Neeſ Pallas: That no vnruly body or diſquiet, diſturb the nobl aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blée, or els be ons ſo bolld too enter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Caſti gatez. Awey with al raſcallz, captiuez, mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cholik, waiward, froward, Coniurerz, and Uſurers, and to haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borers and vnderwoorkmen for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of ony place, alwey at hand az they ſhoold be commaunded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iupiter.</hi> Sent parſonagez of hy honor &amp; dignitée: Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Lords, Ladies, Iuges <note place="margin">Iupiter.</note> Biſhops, Lawyerz, Doctors: with them, vertu, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>obl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſ, equitée, liberalitée &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8645:30"/>
due ſeazo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; fayr weather: ſauing that at the petition of hiz déer ſiſter <hi>Ceres,</hi> he grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted a day or too of ſum ſwéet ſhoourz for rypening of her corn that waz ſo well ſet, &amp; too ſet forward harueſt: Heerwith, beſtoed he ſuch plenty of pleazaunt thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, lightning, &amp; thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derbollts: by hiz hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſun &amp; fyermaſter, <hi>Vulcan</hi> ſtil freſh &amp; freſh framed: alweyz ſo frequent, ſo intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labl, &amp; of ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuauns in the ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding (az I partly tolld ye) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed<hi>:</hi> that ſurely he ſéemz too be az of poour ineſtimabl: ſo, in ſtore of municion, vnwaſtabl: For all <hi>Ouids</hi> cenſure that ſaiz.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Si quoties peccant homines ſua fulmina mittat</l>
               <l>Iupiter: exig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o tempore inermis erit.</l>
            </q>
            <l>If Ioue ſhoold ſhoot hiz thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derbollts az oft az me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offend,</l>
            <l>Aſſure yoo hiz artillary wold ſoon be at an end</l>
            <p>What a number of eſtatez &amp; of nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litée had <hi>Iupiter</hi> aſſembled thear, geſſ yée by this: that of ſort woorſhipfull thear wear in the coourt dayly aboode fourty, whearof the meyneſt, of a thoouza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mark yéerly reuenu, and many of mooch more. This great gyft byſide, did hiz deitée caſt vpon her highnes, too haue fayr &amp; ſeazo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabl weather at her ooun appointment:
<pb facs="tcp:8645:31"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 lines">
                  <desc>〈4 lines〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, made humbl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ute vntoo her highnes too cum: too ſuch whearof as her maieſty coold, it cam: and they ſeazon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptabl.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phoebus,</hi> Biſide his continuall &amp; moſt <note place="margin">Phoebus.</note> delicious muzik (az I haue toold yoo) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed he Princes too adoourn her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes coourt, Coounſelerz, Herauds, and ſanguine yooth, pleazaunt &amp; mery, coſtlye garments, learned Phizicianz, &amp; no néede of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuno,</hi> Golld cheynez, Ouchez, Iewels <note place="margin">Iuno.</note> of gret price &amp; rich attyre, woorn in mooch grace &amp; good beſéeming without pryde, or emulacion of ony.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mars.</hi> Captainz of good conduct, Men <note place="margin">Mars.</note> ſkylfull in feats of armz, pollitik in ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagemz, Good coorage in good quarelz, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant, &amp; wizehardy: Abandoning pikquar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels &amp; ruffianz: appoynting alſo Purſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts, currarz &amp; poſts ſtill féeding her highnes with nuze &amp; intelligencez from all parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Venus.</hi> Vntoo the Ladyez &amp; Gentl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wemen: <note place="margin">Venus.</note>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:8645:31"/>
:beauty, good fauour, cumlineſſe, gala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t attyre, dauncing with cumly grace ſwéet vois in ſong &amp; pleazaunt tallk with expreſſ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment &amp; charge vntoo her ſunn on her bleſſing, that he ſhoote not a ſhaft in the Coourt all the while her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes remayned at Killingwoorth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercuri.</hi> Learned men in Sciencez, Poets, Merchaunts, Painterz, Karuerz, <note place="margin">Mercuri</note> Players, Engyners, Deuyſerz &amp; dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tée in handling of all pleazaunt attempts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luna.</hi> Callm nights for quiet reſt, and ſyluer moonſhine, that nightly in déede <note place="margin">Luna.</note> ſhone for moſt of her Maieſtyez béeing thear.</p>
            <p>Blinde <hi>Plutus.</hi> Bags of moony, Cuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merz. <note place="margin">Plutus.</note> Exchaungers, Bankers, Store of riches in plate and in coyn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bacchus.</hi> Full Cups euery whear, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">Bacchus.</note> oour of al kynds of wyne.</p>
            <p>Thear waz no deintée that the Sea coold yéeld, but <hi>Neptune</hi> (thoough hiz <note place="margin">Neptune.</note> reign at the néereſtly well ny a hundred mile of) did dayly ſend in great plenty, ſwéet and freaſh. As for freaſhwater fiſh, the ſtore of all ſorts waz aboundaunt.</p>
            <p>And hoow bountiful <hi>Ceres</hi> in prouizion <note place="margin">Cere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> waz, geſſ ye by this: that in lyttl more then
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8645:32"/>
a thrée dayz ſpace, 72. tunn of Ale &amp; Bée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> waz pyept vp quite: what that mighte whilſt with it of bread beſide meat, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me to yoo. And yet maſter Control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, maſter Coferar and diuerz officers of the Coourt, ſum honorabl, and ſundrye right woorſhipfull placed at Warwik for more rooum in the Caſtl. But heer was no ho Maſter Martin in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoout drinking allwey: that brought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lak vnlookt for, which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being knoen too the Woorſhipfull my Lords good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boourz, cam thear in a too dayz ſpace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſundry friendz: a reléef of a xl. tunn, till a nu ſupply was gotten agayn: and then too oour drinking a freſhe az faſt az euer we did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flora.</hi> Abrode &amp; within the hoous mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred <note place="margin">Flora.</note> of flourz ſo great a quantitée: of ſuch ſwéet ſauoour, ſo beautifully hued, ſo large and fayr of proporcion, and of ſo ſtraunge kindez &amp; ſhapez, that it waz great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure too ſée: &amp; ſo mooch the more, az thear waz great ſtore yet counterfet &amp; foormed of featherz by art, lyke glorioous too the ſheaw az wear the naturall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Protheus.</hi> Hiz Tumbler that coold <note place="margin">Protheus.</note> by nimblneſſ caſt himſelf intoo ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8645:32"/>
foorms &amp; facionz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pan.</hi> Hiz mery morrys dauns with their <note place="margin">Pan.</note> pype &amp; taber.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellona.</hi> Her quintine knights &amp; proper <note place="margin">Bellona<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> bickerings of the Couentrée men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polyphemus. Neptunez</hi> ſun &amp; heyr (let <note place="margin">Polyphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> him I pray &amp; it be but for hiz fathers ſake and for his good wyll, be allowed for a God, with hiz bearz hiz bear whealps and bandogs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aeolus.</hi> Hollding vp hiz windez while <note place="margin">Aeolus.</note> her highnes at any tyme took pleazure on the water, and ſtaying of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſts during abode héer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Syluanus.</hi> Beu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hiz plentifull prouizion <note place="margin">Syluanus.</note> of fooul for deynty viaunds, his pleazau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſwéet ſinging byrds: whearof I will ſheaw yoo more anon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Echo.</hi> Her wel endighted dialog.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faunus.</hi> Hiz ioly Sauage. <note place="margin">Echo. Faunus. Genius.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Genius loci.</hi> Hiz tempring of al things within &amp; without, with apt tyme &amp; place too pleazure &amp; delight.</p>
            <p>Then the thrée <hi>Charites: Aglaia,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Charites.</note> with her lightſum gladnes. <hi>Thalia</hi> her flooriſhing freſhnes. <hi>Euphroſyne,</hi> her cheerfullnes of ſpirite, and with theez three in one aſſent <hi>Concordia:</hi> with
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8645:33"/>
her amitée and good agréement. That too hoow great effects their poourz wear pooured oout heer among vs, let it bée iudged by this: that by a multytude thus met of a thrée or foour thoouzand e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day: and diuerz dayz more, of ſo ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry degrées, profeſſions, agez, appetytz, diſpozicions &amp; affections: ſuch a drifte of tyme was thear paſſed, with ſuch amitée, looue, paſtime, agréement, and obediens whear it ſhoold: and without quarrel, iar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, grudging, or (that I coold héer) of yll woord betwéen any. A thing maſter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin very rare &amp; ſtraunge, and yet no more ſtraunge then tru.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parcae</hi> (az earſt I ſhoold haue ſayd) <note place="margin">parcae.</note> the firſt night of her Maieſtiez cumming: they héering &amp; ſéeing ſo precioous ado héer at a place vnlookt for, in an vplo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſh cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trée ſo far within the Ream: preaſſing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too euery ſtéed whear her highnes went, whearby ſo duddld with ſuch varietée of delyghts, did fet aſide their huſwifrye, coold not for their harts tend their work a whyt. But after they had ſéen her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty a bed, gat them a prying into euery place olld hags, az fond of nuellries, az yoong girls that had neuer ſéen Court a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8645:33"/>
but neyther full, with gazing nor wery with gadding, leaft of yet for that time, and at high midnight, gat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them gigling, (but not alooud) into the prezens Chamber: minding indéed with their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zent diligens, too recompens their former ſtaknes.</p>
            <p>So, ſetting them ſeluez thus dooun too their woork: alas ſayz <hi>Atropos</hi> I haue loſt my ſhéerz: <hi>Lacheſis</hi> laught apace and woold not draw a thréed: And thinke ye damez that ile hoold the diſtaff whyle both y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſit idle? why no by my mootherz ſoll qd. <hi>Clotho.</hi> Thearwith fayr lapt in a fine lawn the ſpindel and rok, that waz dizend with pure purpl ſylk, layd they ſafely vp toogyther: that of hir Maieſtyez diſtaff for an eightéen dayz, thear waz not a thréed ſpoon I aſſure you.</p>
            <p>The too ſyſters after that, (I hard ſay) began their woork again: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> long may they continu, but <hi>Atropos</hi> hard no tydings of her ſhéers, and not a man that moned her loſſ. She iz not belooued ſurely, for this can I tell yoo: that whither it bee for hate too the hag, or looue to her highnes, or els for both: euery man prayz God ſhe may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer find them for that woork, and ſo pray I daily
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:8645:34"/>
apted in all pointes to the beſt.</p>
            <p>Vntoo thiz, hiz honorz exquiſit appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">The Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note> of a beautifull Garden, an aker or more of quantitee that lyeth on the north thear. Whearin hard all along the Caſtl wall iz reared a pleazaunt Teries of a ten foot hy &amp; a twelue brode: éeuen vnder foot &amp; freſh of fyne graſſ: az iz allſo the ſide thearof toward the gardein, in whiche by ſundry equall diſtauncez: with obeliſks, ſphearz, and white bearz all of ſtone vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr curioouz baſez, by goodly ſhew wear ſet: too theez, too fine arbers redolent by ſwéet trées and floourz, at ech end one, the garden plot vnder that, with fayr alleyz gréen by graſſ, éeuen voided from the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derz a both ſydez, and ſum (for chaunge) with ſand, not light or to ſoft, or ſoilly by duſt, but ſmooth and fyrme, pleaſaunt too walk on, az a ſea ſhore when the water iz auaild: then, much gracified by du pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porcion of four éeuen quarterz: in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt of each, vpon a baſe a too foot ſquare, &amp; hy, ſéemly borderd of it ſelf, a ſquare pilaſter rizing pyramidally of a fyftéen foote hy: Simmetrically pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rced through fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a foot beneath, vntill a too foot of the top: whear vpon, for a Capitell, an Orb of a ten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8645:34"/>
thik: euery of théez (with hiz baſe) from the groound too the top of one hole pées, heawen oout of hard Porphiry, and with great art &amp; héed (thinks me) thyther conuey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; thear erected.</p>
            <p>Whear further allſo by great caſt &amp; coſt the ſwéetnes of ſauoour on all ſidez, made ſo reſpiraunt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the redolent plants and fragra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t earbs and floourz, in foorm, cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and quantitée ſo delicioouſly variant: and frute Trées bedecked with their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plz, Peares and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe Cherryez.</p>
            <p>And vnto theez in the midſt, agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Cage</note> Terres: a ſquare cage, ſumptuoous and beautifull, ioyned hard to the Northwall (that a that ſide gards the gardein, as the gardein the Caſtl) of a rare form and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency was reyzed: in heyth a twentye foot, thyrty long, and a foourtéen brode. From the ground ſtrong &amp; cloſe, reared breaſt hy, whear at a ſoyl of a fayr mool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding was coouched all abaout: From that vpward, foour great wyndoz a froont and too at each éend, euery one a fyue foot wide, az many mo éeuen abooue them, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided on all parts by a tranſum and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitraue ſo likewize raunging aboout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cage. Each windo arched in the top, and
<pb facs="tcp:8645:35"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 lines">
                  <desc>〈3 lines〉</desc>
               </gap> touched a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> along vpon y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hole ſquare. Which with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nit, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhez ſixe ſquare, an inch wyde (az it wear for a flat roof) and likewiſe the ſpace of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery windo with great cunning and cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen and tight waz al ouerſtrained V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der the Corniſh again, euery part beau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifyed with great Diamons, Emerauds, Rubyes and Saphyres: poynted, tabld, rok and roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd garniſht with their golld, by ſkilfull hed and hand, and by toile and penſill, ſo lyuely expreſt, az it mought bee great marueil and pleaſure to conſider how neer excellency of art could approch vntoo perfection of nature.</p>
            <p>Bear with me good euntréeman thoogh thinges be not ſheawd heer az well az I woold, or az well as they ſhoold. For in déed I can better imagin &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyue that I ſée, then wel vtter or duly declare it. Holez wear thear alſo and cauerns in orderly di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtauns &amp; facion, voyded intoo the wall az wel for heat, for coolnes, for rooſt a nightz &amp; refuge in weather, az allſo for breeding when tyme iz. More, fayr eeuen and freſh
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8645:35"/>
holly treez for pearching and proining ſet within, tooward each eend one. Heereto their diuerſitée of meats, theyr fine ſeueral veſſels for their water, and ſundry grainz. And a man ſkilful and diligent to looke too them and tend them.</p>
            <p>But (ſhall I tell yoo) the ſiluer ſoounded Lute, withoout the ſwéet toouch of hand: the glorioous goollden cup, withoout the freſh fragrant wine, or the rich ring with gem, without the fayr feawtered fynger: iz nothing indéede in hiz proper grace &amp; vſe: Euen ſo his Honor accounted of thiz manſion, till he had plaſt thear tenauntes according. Had it thearfore repleniſhte with liuely Burds, Engliſh, French, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, Canarian, and (I am deceaued if I ſaw not ſum) African. Whearby, whither it becam more delightſum in chaunge of tunez and armony too the eare: or els in differens of coolerz, kyndez &amp; propertyez too the ey, Ile tell yoo if I can whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue better be thought me.</p>
            <p>One day (Maſter Martin) az the Gardin <note place="margin">The Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> door waz open, &amp; her highnes a hunting by licens of my good fréend Adria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I cam in at a bek, but woold ſkant oout with a thruſt: for ſure I waz loth ſo ſoon to depart.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:8645:36"/>
Well may this (Maſter Martyn) bee ſuinwhat too magnitude of mynde, but more thearof az ye ſhall kno, more cauz ye ſhall haue ſo too think: heer out what I tel yoo, and tell me when we méet.</p>
            <p>In the center (az it wear) of this goodly <note place="margin">The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</note> Gardein, was theer placed a very fayre Foountain, caſt intoo an eight ſquare, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a four foot hy, from the midſt whear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Colum vp ſet in ſhape of too <hi>Ath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants</hi> ioined togeather a backhalf, the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n looking Eaſt, toother Weſt, with theyr hands vphollding a fayr formed boll of a thrée foot ouer: from wheans ſundrye fine pipez, did liuely diſtill continuall ſtreamz intoo the receyt of the Foountayn: mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned ſtyll too foot déep by the ſame freſh falling water: whearin pleazauntly play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too &amp; fro &amp; round about Carp, Tench, Bream, and for varietée, Pearch &amp; Eel, fyſh fayrliking all and large, in the toppe the ragged ſtaffe: which, with the boll, the pillar, and eyght ſides beneath, wear all heawen oout of rich &amp; hard white Marbl. A one ſyde, <hi>Neptune</hi> with hiz <hi>Tridental Fuskin</hi> triumphing in hiz Throne, tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into the déep by his marine horſez.</p>
            <p>On an other, <hi>Thetis</hi> in her chariot drawn
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8645:36"/>
by her Dollphins. Then <hi>Triton</hi> by hiz fyſhez. Héer <hi>Protheus</hi> hearding hiz ſea buls. Thear <hi>Doris</hi> &amp; her dooughterz ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacyng a ſea &amp; ſandz. The wauez ſoour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with froth &amp; fome, entermengled in place, with whalez, whirlpoolz, ſturgeonz, Tunneyz, Couchs &amp; wealks: all engraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by exquiſit deuize and ſkill, ſo az I maye thinke this not much inferioour vntoo <hi>Phoebus</hi> gatez, which <hi>(Ouid</hi> ſayz) &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduentur a pattern to thiz, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Vulcan</hi> him <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Metam.</hi> 2</note> ſelf dyd cut: whearof ſuch was the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of art, that the woork in valu ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moounted the ſtuff, and yet wer the gatez all of clean maſſy ſyluer.</p>
            <p>Héer wear thinges ye ſee moought en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame ony mynde too long after looking: but whoo ſo was found ſo hot in deſyre, with the wreaſt of a Cok was ſure of a coolar: water ſpurting vpward with ſuch vehemency, az they ſhoold by &amp; by be moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtned from top too to. The hées to ſum laughing, but the ſhées to more ſport. Thiz ſumtime waz occupied to very good paſtime.</p>
            <p>A Garden then ſo appoynted, az whearin a loft vpon ſwéet ſhadoed wallk of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, in heat of Soomer, too féel the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaunt
<pb facs="tcp:8645:37"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>tabl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ith: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>lks: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ourz <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>urz: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, the waters (for both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; chaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hard at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight) the deer, the peepl (that oout of the Gaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe coourt, allſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hande in view) the frute trées, the plants, the earbs, the floourz, the chaunge in coolers, the Burds flyttering, the Foountaine ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, the Fyſh ſwymming: all in ſuch delectabl varietée, order dignitée: whear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by at one moment in one place, at hande <note place="margin">Paradiſus. Giaec. Hortus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. Aut He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es id eſt. Hortus.</note> without trauell too haue ſo full fruition of ſo many Gods bleſſinges, by entyer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light vnto al ſencez (if al ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take) at ones: for <hi>Etymon</hi> of the woord woorthy to bée calld Paradys: and though not ſo goodly az Paradis for want of the fayr Riuers, yet better a great deel by the lak of ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy a trée. Argument moſt certein of a right nobl minde, that in this ſort coold
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8645:37"/>
haue thus all contriued.</p>
            <p>But Maſter Martin, yet one wyndleſſe muſt I featch, too make ye one more fayr coors and I can: and cauz I ſpeak of one: let me tel yoo a littl of the dignitée of one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod, <note place="margin">The nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whearin allweyz, al hy Deitee al So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraintee, Préeminens, Principalitee and Concord withoout poſſibilitee of diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment iz conteyned. Az one God, one Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioour, one Feith, one Prins, one Sun, one Phenix, and az one of great wizdom ſayz: one hart one wey. Whear onehod reinz: ther quiet bears rule, &amp; diſcord fliez a paſe. Thrée again may ſignify cumpany, a méeting, a multitude, pluralitée: ſo az all talez and numbrings fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too vntoo three, and ſo vpward, may well be counted num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berz, till they moount vntoo infinitée, or els too confuſion, which thing the ſum of Too can neuer admit: nor it ſelf can well bee coounted a number, but rather a freendly coniunction of too ones, that keeping in a ſynceritee of accord, may purport vnto vs, Charitée each too other, mutuall looue, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréement &amp; integritée of friendſhip with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oout diſſimulation. Az iz in théez. The too Teſtamentes. The too Tables of the Law. The too great lights: <hi>Duo lumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8645:38"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>k <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>z <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>: Az fy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt for paſtymez ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s and hawks: déer, red &amp; fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, hare &amp; for, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trich &amp; fezaunt, fyſh &amp; fooul, carp &amp; tench. For warz, ſpear &amp; ſhéeld, hors &amp; harneis, ſwoord &amp; bukler: for ſuſtenauns, wheat &amp; barly, peaz and beanz, meat and drinke, bread &amp; meat, béer &amp; ale, appis and pearz.</p>
            <p>But leaſt by ſuch dualitéez I draw yoo too far: let vs heer ſtay, and cum néerer home. Sée what a ſort of fréendly bini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téez we oour ſeluez doo conſiſt &amp; ſtond vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Fyrſt oour too feet, too legs, too knéez, ſo vpward: and abooue, too ſhoolderz, too armz &amp; too ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. But chéefly our principll Too, that iz, body and ſoll: then in the hed whear all oour ſenſez méet, and allmoſt all in Tooz: too nozethrills, too earz and too eyz So ar we of fréendly Tooz, from top too to. Wel, to this number of bini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téez,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8645:38"/>
take ye one mo for an vpſhot, &amp; heer an eend. Too Dyallz ny vnto the battil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <note place="margin">The too Diallz.</note> ar ſet aloft vpon too of the ſidez of Cezarz toour one Eaſt, thoother Soouth for ſo ſtond they beſt to ſheaw the oourz too the tooun &amp; cuntrée: both fayre large and rich, by vyſe for groou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; goold for letterz whearby they glitter conſpicuous a great wey of. The clokbell that iz good &amp; ſhrill, waz commaunded too ſilens at firſt, and in deede ſang not a note all the while her highnes waz thear, the clok ſtood alſo ſtill withall. But mark noow, whither wear it by chauns, by conſtellation of ſtarz, or by fatall appoyntment (if fatez and ſtarz doo deal with dialz.) Thus waz it in déede: The handz of both the tablz ſtood firm and <note place="margin">The Diallz at ii. a clok.</note> faſt, allweyz poynting too iuſt too a clok, ſtill at too a clok. Which thing beholding by hap at firſt<hi>:</hi> but after ſeriouſly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in déed, enprinted intoo me a déepe ſign &amp; argument certein. That thiz thing amoong the reſt, waz for full ſignifiauns of his Lordſhips, honorabl, fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k, frendly, and nobl hart toward al eſtates. Which, whither cum they to ſtay &amp; take chéer, or ſtraight to returne: too ſee, or to be ſéene: cum they for duty too her Maieſty or looue
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8645:39"/>
too hiz Lordſhip, or for both: Cum they early or late: for his Lordſhips part, they cum allweyz all at too a clok een iump at too a clok<hi>:</hi> That iz to ſay in good harte, good acceptauns, in amitée and freendlye wellcoom. Who ſaw els that I ſaw, in right muſt ſay az I ſay. For ſo manye thinges byſide, Maſter Humfrey wear heerin ſo conſonant vnto my conſtruction, that thiz poynting of the clok (to my ſelf) I took in amitée as an oracle certain. And heer iz my windleſſe, lyke yoor coorſe as pleaz ye.</p>
            <p>But noow ſyr too cum to eend. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing of her hignes, and entertainment of all thoother eſtatez. Syns of delicatez that ony wey mought ſerue or delight: az of wyne, ſpice, deynty viaunds, plate Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zik, ornaments of hoous, rich arras &amp; ſyth (too ſay nothing of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meaner thinges) the maſſ by prouizion waz heaped ſo hoouge, which the boounty in ſpending did after bewray. The conceit ſo déep in caſting the plat at firſt. Such a wizdom and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in acquiring things ſo rich, ſo rare, and in ſuch abundauns: by ſo imm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ens &amp; profuſe a charge of expens, whiche by ſo honorabl ſeruis &amp; exquiſit order, curteizy
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8645:39"/>
of officerz and humanitée of al, wear after ſo boountifully beſtoed and ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, what may this expreſſ, what may this ſet oout vntoo vs, but only a magnifyk minde, a ſinguler wizdoom, a prinſly ꝓurs, and an heroicall hart? If it wear my theam Maſter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn, too ſpeake of hiz Lordſhips great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor &amp; magnificens, though it be not in me too ſay ſufficiently, az bad a penclark az I am, yet coold I ſay a great deel more.</p>
            <p>But being heer now in magnificens, &amp; matters of greatnes: it falz wel too mynd. The greatnes of his honors Tent, that <note place="margin">The great Tent.</note> for her Maieſtyez dining was pighte at long Ichington, the day her highnes cam to Killing worth Caſtl. A tabernacl indéed for number and ſhift of large and goodlye roomz, for fayr &amp; eazy offices both inward &amp; ooutward al ſo likeſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in order &amp; eyſight: that iuſtly for dignitée may be comparabl with a beautifull Pallais, &amp; for greatnes &amp; qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titée with a proper tooun, or rather a Cittadell. But to be ſhort, leaſt I kéepe yoo too long from the Ryall Exchaunge noow, and too cauz yoo conceyue mooche matter in feaweſt woordes. the Iron bedſted of Og the King of Baſan (ye wot) waz foour yards and a halfe long, and too <note place="margin">Deut.</note>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:8645:40"/>
yards wide, whearby ye conſider a Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt of a great proportion waz he. This Tent had ſeauen cart lode of pynz pertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning too it: noow for the greatneſſ, geſſ az ye can.</p>
            <p>And great az it waz (too marſhall oour matters of greatnes togither) not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Weather at Grafton, brought too the Coort, that for body and wooll was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding great, the meazure I tooke not, let me ſheaw you with what great marueyl a great Chyld of Leyceter ſhire, at this lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Ichington, by the Parents waz prezen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: great (I ſay) of limz &amp; proportion, of a foour foot &amp; foour inches hy: and els lanuginoous az a lad of eyghtéen yeerz, béeing indeede auowd too be but ſix yéer olld: nothing more bewraying hiz age the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hiz wit: that waz, az for thooz yeers ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl &amp; childiſh.</p>
            <p>Az for vnto hiz Lordſhip, hauing with ſuch greatnes of honorabl modeſtye &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitée ſo paſſed foorth, as <hi>Laude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidia et an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icos par arit.</hi> By greatneſſe of <note place="margin">Terent.</note> well dooing, woon with all ſorts to bée in ſuch reuerens, az: <hi>De quo me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiri fama ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur.</hi> In ſynceritée of fréendſhip ſo great, <note place="margin">Bias.</note> az no man more deuooutly woorſhips.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:8645:40"/>
               <hi>Illud amicitiae ſanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et veneral ile nomen.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> So great in liberalitie, az hath no wey to heap vp the maſſ of hiz trezure, but only by liberal gyuing &amp; boounteoous beſtoing hiz trezure: foloing (az it ſéemez) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaw of Martiall that ſayth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Extra fortuna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, quicquid donatur amicis</l>
               <l>Quas dederis, ſolas ſemper habebis opes.</l>
            </q>
            <l>Oout of all hazer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d dooſt thou ſet that to thy freends thoou gyueſt:</l>
            <l>A ſurer trezure canſt thoou not haue euer whyle thoou lyueſt.</l>
            <p>What may théez greatneſſes bode, but only az great honor, fame, &amp; renooum for théez parts héer awey, az euer waz vntoo thoz too nobl Greatz: the Macedonian A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der in Emathia or grées, or to Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Charles in Germanye, or Italy? which, wear it in me ony wey to ſet oout, no man of all men by God (Maſter Martin) had euer more cauz, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> héerby conſider yoo. It pleazed his honor to beare me good wil at fyrſt, &amp; ſo too continu. To haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me apparail éeuen from hiz bak, to get me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowauns in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtabl, too aduauns me vntoo this worſhipfull office ſo néer the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norabl Councell, to help me in my licens of Beanz (though indéed I do not ſo much vze it, for I thank God I néed not) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my good Father to ſerue the ſtabl.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8645:41"/>

               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="11 lines">
                  <desc>〈11 lines〉</desc>
               </gap> by your leaue while God le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to vtter my minde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hauing az good cauz of his honor, az <hi>Virgil</hi> had of <hi>Auguſtus Cezar)</hi> wil, I poet it a littl with <hi>Virgill,</hi> and ſay.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Namque erit ille mihi ſeper Deus, illius ara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Sepe tener nostris ab ouilibus imbuet agnus. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eglog.</hi> 1.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <l>For he ſhall be a god to me, till death my life conſumez:</l>
            <l>His auters will I ſacrifice with incens and parfumez.</l>
            <p>A ſingular patr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of humanitée may he be well vnto vs towarde all degréez: of Honor, toward hy Eſtates, and chéeflye whearby we may learne in what dignitée, worſhip and reuerens her highnes iz to be eſteemed, honored and receiued, that waz neuer indéed more condignly doon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> héer ſo as neither by the bylders at firſt, nor by
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8645:41"/>
the Edict of pacification after, was euer <note place="margin">1266. <hi>An.</hi> 50. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.</note> Kenelworth more nobled then by thiz, hiz Lordſhips receiui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hir highnes héer now.</p>
            <p>But Ieſu Ieſu whither am I drawen noow. But tallk I of my Lord onz, éen thus it farez with me: I forget all, my fréends, &amp; my ſelf too. And yet yoo, being a Mercer, a Merchant, az I am: my cuntrée man born, &amp; my good fréend withal, whear by I kno ye ar compaſſiond with me: Me thought it my part ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what to empart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yoo, hoow it iz héer with me, &amp; hoow I lead my life, which in déed iz this.</p>
            <p>A mornings I rize ordinartly at ſeauen a clok: Then reddy, I go intoo the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: ſoon after eyght, I get me commonly intoo my Lords Chamber, or intoo my Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prezidents. Thear at the cupboord after I haue eaten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manchet, ſerued ouer night for liuery (for I dare be az bolld, I promis yoo, az any of my freends the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts thear: and indéed coold I haue freſh if I woold tary, but I am of woont iolly &amp; dry a mornings) I drink me vp a good bol of Ale: when in a ſwéet pot it iz defecated by al nights ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, the drink iz y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better, take that of me: &amp; a morſell in a morning with a ſound draught iz very holſome and good for the eyſight. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am az freſh all the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:8645:42"/>
y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> forenoon after, az had I eaten a hole pées of béef. Noow ſyr, if the Councell ſit. I am at hand, wait at an inch I warrant yoo If any make babling, peas (ſay I) woot ye whear ye ar? if I take a lyſtenar, or a priar in at the chinks or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lokhole, I am by &amp; by in the bones of him, but now they kéep good order, they kno me well mough: If a be a fréend or ſuch one az I lyke: I make him ſit dooun by me on a foorm, or a cheaſt, let the reſt walk a Gods name. And héer doth my langagez now and than ſtond me in good ſted, my Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, my Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſh, my Dutch, &amp; my Latten: ſumtime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moong Ambaſſadours me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if their Maſter be within with the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, ſumtime with the Ambaſſadour himſelf, if hee bid call hiz lacky, or aſk me whats a clok, and I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ye I aunſwer him roundly that they maruell to ſée ſuch a fello thear: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laugh I &amp; ſay nothing. Dinner &amp; ſupper I haue twenty placez to go to, &amp; hartly prayd to: And ſumtime get I too Maſter Pinner by my faith a worſhipfull Gentlman, and az carefull for his charge az ony hir highnez hath: thear find I alway good ſtore of very good viaunds we eat and bee merry thank God &amp; the Quéene. Himſelf in féeding ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry temperat &amp; moderat az ye ſhall ſée ony:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8645:42"/>
and yet by your leaue of a diſh, az a colld pigeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſo, that hath cum to him at meat more then he lookt for, I haue ſéen him éen ſo by and by ſurfit, az he hath pluct of hiz napkin, wyept his knife, &amp; eat not a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell more: lyke ynoough to ſtik in hiz ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make a too dayz after: (Sum hardmeſſage from the higher officers, perceiue ye me?) Vpon ſearch, hiz faithfull dealing and dili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gens hath found him fautles. In after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noons &amp; a nights, ſumtime am I with the right worſhipfull Sir George Howard, az good a Gentlman as ony liuez: And ſumtime at my good Lady Sidneis cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, a Noblwooman that I am az mooch boound vntoo, as ony poore man may bee vnto ſo gracyons a Lady: And ſumtime in ſum oother place. But alwayez among the Gentlwemen by my good will (O, yée kno that cum alweyez of a gentle ſpirite) &amp; when I ſée cumpany according than can I be az lyuely to, ſumtyme I foote it with daunſing: noow with my Gitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rn, and els with my Cittern, then at the Virgynalz: Ye kno nothing cums amiſſe to mée: then carroll I vp a ſong withall: that by and by they com flocking about me lyke béez too hunny: and euer they cry, anoother good Langham anoother. Shall I tell yoo?
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8645:43"/>
when I ſée Miſterz—(A, ſée a madde knaue, I had almoſt tollde all) that ſhee gyuez onz but an ey or an ear: why then, man, am I b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt, my grace, my corage, my cunning iz doobled: She ſayz ſumtime ſhe likez it, &amp; then I like it mooch the better, it dooth me good to heer hoow well I can doo. And too ſay truth: what, with myne eyz. az I can amoroouſly gloit it, with my ſpaniſh ſoſpires, my french heigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, mine Italian dulcets, my dutch houez my doobl <note place="margin">vp ſyn houe</note> releas, my hy reachez, my fine feyning, my déep diapaſon, my wanton warblz, my running, my tyming, my tuning and my twynkling, I can gracify the matters az well az the prowdeſt of them, and waz yet neuer ſtaynd I thank God. By my troth cuntreman it iz ſumtim hy midnight ear I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> get from them. And thus haue I told ye moſt of my trade, al the léeue long daye: what will ye more, God ſaue the Quéene, and my Lord, I am well I thank yoo.</p>
            <p>Hée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with ment I fully to bid ye farewell, had not this doubt cum to my minde, that heer remainz a doout in yoo, which I ought (me thought) in any wyze to cléer. Which, iz, ye maruel perchauns to ſée me ſo bookiſh. Let me tell yoo in, few woords: I went to ſcool forſooth both at Pollez, &amp;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8645:43"/>
allſo at ſaint Antoniez: in the fifth foorm, paſt Eſop fabls iwys, red Terens. <hi>Vos iſtaec intro auferte,</hi> &amp; began with my Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill <hi>Tytire tu patulae.</hi> I coold my rulez coold conſter &amp; pars with the beſt of them ſyns, that (az partly ye kno) haue I trades the feat of marchaundize in ſundry Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyz, &amp; ſo gat me Langagez: which do ſo littl hinder my Latten, az (I thank God) haue mooch encreaſt it. I haue leizure ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, when I tend not vpon the coounſell: whearby, now look I on one booke, noow on an other. Stories I delight in the more auncient &amp; rare, the more likeſum vntoo me: If I tolld ye, I lyked<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> William a Malmeſbery ſo well, bicauz of hiz diligenz &amp; antiquitée. Perchauns ye woold conſter it bicauz I loue Mamzey ſo well: but I feith it iz not ſo: for ſipt I no more Sak &amp; ſuger (&amp; yet neuer but with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I doo Malmzey, I ſhould not bluſh ſo moch a dayz as I doo, ye kno my minde. Well noow thus fare ye hartily well: yfeith, if with wiſhig it coold haue béen, ye had had a buk or too this ſoomer, but we ſhal cum neerer ſhortly, &amp; then ſhal we merely méet &amp; grace a God, in the mean time comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me I beſek yo: vntoo my good freends, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt moſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yoor neighbors. Maſter
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:8645:44"/>
Aſſderman Pulliſon, a ſpeciall fréend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of mine: and in ony wiſe too my good old freend Maſter Smith Cuſtumer, by that ſame token. Set my hors vp too the rak, &amp; then lets haue a cup of Sak. He knoez the token well ynough, &amp; wil laugh, I hold ye a grote. Too Maſter Thorogood: And too my mery cumpanion (a Mercer ye wot az we be) Maſter Denman, <hi>Mio fratello in Chriſto:</hi> he iz woont too ſummon me by the name of Ro. La. of the Coounty No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham Gentlman, A good companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I feyth. Well onez again fare ye hartely well. From the Coourt. At the Citée of Worceter, the xx of Auguſt. 1575.</p>
            <p>Yoor countréeman, companion, &amp; freend-aſſuredly: Mercer, Merchantauenturer, and Clark of the Counſel chamber door, and alſo kéeper of the ſame: <hi>El Prencipe negro.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Par me</hi> R. L. Gent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mercer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>DE MAIESTATE REGIA Benigno.</head>
            <l>Cedant arma togae, concedat laurea lingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,</l>
            <l>Iactanter Cicero, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iustius illud habe:</l>
            <l>Ceda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t arma togae, vigil et toga cedat honori</l>
            <l>Omnia concedant Imperio<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuo.</l>
            <closer>DEO OPT. MAX. GRATIAE</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8645:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
